<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Paidobaptismos orthobaptismos: or, The baptism of infants vindicated by scriptures and reasons Humbly offered in order to a composure of differences at this juncture of time. By Nath. Taylor, M.A.</title>
            <author>Taylor, Nathanael, d. 1702.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 145 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 53 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A64230</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T544A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R222422</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99833600</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99833600</idno>
            <idno type="VID">38078</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A64230)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 38078)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2179:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Paidobaptismos orthobaptismos: or, The baptism of infants vindicated by scriptures and reasons Humbly offered in order to a composure of differences at this juncture of time. By Nath. Taylor, M.A.</title>
                  <author>Taylor, Nathanael, d. 1702.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 96 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Richard Butler next door to the Lamb and Three Bowls in Barbican,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The first two words of title are in Greek characters.</note>
                  <note>Pages stained with print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the John Rylands University Library of Manchester.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Infant baptism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:38078:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <head type="sub">The Author's diſtance from the Preſs hath occaſioned ſome Miſtakes, which the kind Reader is deſired to Correct.</head>
            <p>TItle Page, read <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, not <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. pag 5. l. 1. r. Practices. p. 17. l. 11. r. God for end. p. 21. l. 7. r. is ſtrong enough. p. 27. l. 7. r. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended. p. 40. l. 3. <hi>dele</hi> 6. p. 58. l. 27. for have, r. heart. p. 61. <hi>in Marg.</hi> for <hi>Wyer,</hi> r. <hi>Wyvel.</hi> p 62. l. 20. for alone, r. along. p. 63. l. 5. for to, r. by. p. 86. l. 7. <hi>dele</hi> in. p. 87. l. 2. <hi>dele</hi> by. p. 91. <hi>Marg.</hi> for <hi>Halak.</hi> r. <hi>Habak.</hi> p. 94. l. 7. r. it is an. p. 95. l. 8. r. <hi>An Earneſt.</hi> and l. 20. r. Give and forgive. p. 96. l. 17. for Active, r. alive. p. 101. l. 28. r. in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible Grace. p. 109. l. 22. 23. r. of, and <hi>dele</hi> and. p. 118. l. 23. for <hi>Omne Corpus,</hi> r. <hi>cum E Corpo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> p. 122. l. 18. for Diviners, r. <hi>Divi</hi> were. p. 129. l. 15. for <hi>Fumus,</hi> r. <hi>Funus.</hi> and l. 18. r. <hi>manſueti.</hi> p. 130. l. 11. for <hi>fides,</hi> r. <hi>fide.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:38078:1"/>
            <p>ΠΑΙΔΟΒΑ'ΠΤΙΣΜΟΣ 'ΟΡΘΟΒΑ'ΠΤΙΣΜΟΣ: OR, THE BAPTISM OF INFANTS Vindicated by Scriptures and Reaſons. Humbly offered in Order to a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſure of Differences at this Juncture of Time.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Nath. Taylor,</hi> M. A.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Mark 10.13.</hi>
                  </bibl> And they brought young Children to him, that he ſhould touch them; and his Diſciples rebuked thoſe that brought them.</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>14.</hi>
                  </bibl> But when Jeſus ſaw it, he was much diſpleaſed, and ſaid unto them, ſuffer the little Children to come unto me, and forbid them not, for of ſuch is the Kingdom of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>15.</hi>
                  </bibl> Verily I ſay unto you, whoſoever ſhall not receive the Kingdom of God as a Little Child, he ſhall not enter therein.</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>16.</hi>
                  </bibl> And he took them up in his Arms, put his Hands upon them, and Bleſſed them.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Butler</hi> next door to the Lamb and Three Bowls in <hi>Barbican,</hi> 1683.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:38078:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:38078:2"/>
            <head>To my Diſſenting Brethren, the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> A perfect underſtanding in all things.</head>
            <p>THE Grand concern of Chriſtianity, and the danger the Proteſtant Religion is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended to be in, by all its Profeſſors, may call for our ſerious Conſiderations, how imprudently we expoſe our ſelves to our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies by our cauſeleſs Diviſions; and how juſtly God (provoked by the Separations and Contentions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong our ſelves) may permit a Wolf to devour us ſcattered Sheep, of which Miſchief I would gladly hope your ſelves grow more ſenſible than for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly ſome of that Party (and they of no ſmall note) having declared by Word, Writing,
<note n="*" place="margin">Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tham's <hi>Friendly Epiſtle to the Biſh. of the Church of</hi> England. Gal. 5.15 Rom. 16.17.</note> and in Print their inclinations to a Compliance with our Church. An Union much to be deſired, and by theſe Pages ſincerely endeavoured for the ſole ends of Gods Glory, and the good of the Souls whoſe unhappi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or Folly I know not which moſt to lament.</p>
            <p>Your unhappineſs in ſeparating from that Church, the Purity of whoſe Doctrine your ſelves do not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, unleſs chiefly in that one Article about Infant Baptiſm; and that hath not been thought cauſe enough to ſeparate from us, by ſeveral, who with your ſelves oppoſed Infant Baptiſm, but wrote a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you for your Separation from our Church on
<pb facs="tcp:38078:3"/>that account,
<note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.</note> thereby hindring your ſelves from the Advantages of a joynt Communion, and expoſing your ſelves to thoſe Judgments Sacred Writ denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth againſt ſuch as cauſe Diviſions.</p>
            <p>Nor yet your Folly (if you pleaſe to excuſe the word) appear leſs upon an impartial enquiry what occaſion, your dividing about Infant Baptiſm. It ſeems to be either about the Subject to be Baptized, or the Mode of Baptizing; for the Eſſence or Form of Baptiſm I may affirm is Practiſed by us more conſonantly to the Commiſſion of our Saviour given to his Apoſtles, <hi>In the Name of the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 28.19.</note> than by you, who give a Liberty (in your Printed Articles) to Baptize <hi>In the Name of Chriſt alone:</hi> The Error of which I have endeavoured to manifeſt.</p>
            <p>And as for the Subject of Baptiſm, the great mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake between us about it, ſeems to ariſe from your not conſidering of, and diſtinguiſhing between the ſtate of Chriſts Church when gathering (in Chriſts and his Apoſtles days) and of it now gathered. For though the Apoſtles could not admit as Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Chriſts Church, either the <hi>Jews,</hi> who Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified our Saviour, or the Heathen, who had not heard of Chriſt, without a preceding Repentance and Profeſſion of Faith by thoſe Adult Perſons to whom they Preached: It being neceſſary they ſhould give a Teſtimony of their Converſion to Chriſt, and believe on Chriſt, before they were Baptized into Chriſt, or owned as Members of his Church.) Yet upon their Converſion, their Children alſo were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived to Baptiſm, according to the will of God under the Law, the extent of the Covenant of Grace and other Arguments urged in this Tract.</p>
            <p>And accordingly our Church (when Heathens or Jews are Converted, or when Parents profeſſing Chriſtianity, bring up their Children unbaptized) doth preſcribe an Inſtructing of them, and a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring from them a Confeſſion of Faith, before
<pb facs="tcp:38078:3"/>they be Baptized. But they being Baptized, our Church (for the ſame Reaſons Gods Church of the <hi>Jews</hi> and Chriſtians ever did) doth receive the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity or Seed of ſuch Converts to Church-mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berſhip and Baptiſm. So that by Chriſtian Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration ye may ſee your Error in Separating from a Church Baptizing Believers as well as you pretend to do.</p>
            <p>As to the Mode of Baptizing, I not a little ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire Men of ſuch Reaſon, as ſome of you are, ſhould ſo place the whole of Baptiſm (a it were) in an external Mode and Circumſtance of its Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration, and that no where expreſſed in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. As to cry up your Dipping for the ſole way of Baptizing, eſteeming ours no Baptiſm, becauſe not ſo performed. Nor can I ſee what cauſe ye can modeſtly plead you have to Separate from our Church, which allows of Dipping or Sprinkling, as being both the import of the word <hi>Baptize,</hi> as will in due time be manifeſted.</p>
            <p>Theſe things conſidered, be pleaſed to take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice how uncharitably ye deal with us, in denying us to be Members of Chriſts Church, or in a viſible way of Salvation, ſo as ye cannot hope we ſhall be ſaved, in the way we are in, thereby expoſing us in your preſent thoughts to Satans Kingdom here, and his Infernal Regions hereafter, from which, that the good Lord would deliver you and us, is my hearty Prayer. And I hope your impartial and conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate peruſal of what is here offered, will more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence your Charity towards us, whoſe Churches Prayers in her laſt Faſt, <hi>Decemb.</hi> 22. 1680. were for all our Unions here, and Glory hereafter.</p>
            <p>And I aſſure you, nothing is in theſe Pages writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with the leaſt deſign of Controverſie, or with the leaſt prejudice againſt any of your Perſons: But ſeriouſly to ſtate the Controverſie,
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.1. <hi>to</hi> 7.</note> and propoſe the Truth, with an earneſt deſire that we who all own the ſame God of Peace, to be Members of the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:38078:4"/>Chriſt,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 13.11. Gal. 5.22. Heb. 12.14. 1 Cor. 3.4.</note> the Prince of Peace, to be acted by the ſame Spirit of Peace, to walk by the ſame Goſpel of Peace, and to enjoy the ſame Heaven hereafter, where we ſhall be at Peace together, may, if poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, be United here, that our Diviſions may no longer rent the Church of Chriſt, to the great hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drance of the Converſion of both <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Gentile,</hi> and the apparent expoſing our Church and State to Ruine and Confuſion by the Fury of our Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. But that our unanimous Prayers may Depre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate apprehended Judgments, and prevail for our continued enjoyment of Goſpel Mercies. And may theſe Pages be in any reſpect ſerviceable to theſe Ends, ſo God have the Glory, and his Church the Advantage, I have my end, who am</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy Faithful Friend.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:38078:4"/>
            <head>The PREFACE TO THE <hi>Paidobaptiſt,</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mongſt the many Parties our Church and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion abounds with, the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> are not the leaſt conſiderable, who not only deny Infant Baptiſm, but proceed ſo far, as to Separate from our Communion on that unwarrantable ground; nor contented with that, they (as if acted by <hi>Infallibility</hi>) confine the Church of Chriſt to their own People, denying our Miniſters to be either Members or Miniſters of Chriſt, and declaring our ſelves and our People to be in no viſible way to Salvation, which ſad expreſſion being daily whiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered into the Ears of the People committed to my Care, did not a little diſturb ſeveral of them, who thus were almoſt ſeduced from our Church. And to add to my trouble, one of the chiefeſt of their Teachers gave me frequent Challenges to a Publick Diſputation, which I declining (as not yet ſeeing any good to have been the iſſue of ſuch Diſputes) he and my Neighbours ſuppoſed my refuſing to diſpute, to preceed from my ſenſe of the weakreſs of the cauſe, or from my inclination to their Opinion.</p>
            <p>Theſe and ſuch like things (Chriſtian Reader) oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned my endeavour to diſcharge my Fidelity to my Peoples Souls, and my own Conſcience, by Publiſhly Preaching on Infant Baptiſm, enquiring into its Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, as to Salvation and Church-memberſhip, in order to the ſatisfying my Peoples troubled minds. And then inquiring into the Form, Subject, and Mode of Baptiſm,
<pb facs="tcp:38078:5"/>to Vindicate the Doctrine and Practice of our Church, and to clear my ſelf of thoſe Aſperſions I met with; which being compleated, I endeavoured to ſolve all thoſe Objections I have yet met with from their Mouths or Writings.</p>
            <p>Which Sermons God was pleaſed to make ſo ſucceſsful, as to ſatisfie my Auditors, ſo that hitherto they have created me no more trouble. And that Perſon who had ſo often Challenged me to Diſpute the Point, having a little private Diſcourſe with me, aſſured me he would no more trouble me or my People, which Promiſe he hath hitherto kept, and hath declared his deſires, and (as he ſaid) the inclination of the moſt Eminent of their Party, to a Compliance with our Church, to promote which, I know there have been ſome endeavours.</p>
            <p>Let then your Candor, I humbly beg, excuſe me, if when God hath been pleaſed to make my Endeavours In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumental to the keeping my People and others from ſtraying from us, if not to reduce ſome from them to our Church. And if after I have been ſometimes requeſted to expoſe my Thoughts, I now at length (finding their inclinableneſs declared by word and writing, to a cloſure with us) humbly offer them, ſuch as they are (after my ſubmitting them to my Dioceſan's Judgment) to the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of Gods Church, in promoting his Glory, and Peace, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion in our days.</p>
            <p>And may my ſincerity in this deſign obtain your Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don for what may be amiſs in this Tract, humbly devoted to the Service of every of your Souls, by one who daily Prays for, and by all endeavours labours to promote the good of our Church and State, it ſhall ever Oblige</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours in the Service of God and Souls.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:38078:5"/>
            <head>Baptiſm OF INFANTS VINDICATED.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Matth. 28.19.</hi>
                     </bibl> Go ye therefore, Teach all Nations, Baptizing them in the Name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>20.</hi>
                     </bibl> Teaching them to obſerve all things whatſoever I have Commanded you.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>OUR Saviour Chriſt, who was the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> promiſed to the <hi>Jews,</hi> and alſo a Saviour Propheſied to the <hi>Gentiles;</hi> being, when manifeſted in the Fleſh, to gather a Church to himſelf
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:38078:6"/>of both <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles,</hi> did while he was on Earth Commiſſionate his Apoſtles to Teach, or Diſciple all Nations, by ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainting them with the Rudments of his Goſpel. And then Ordered the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception of them as Members of his Viſible Church (as by Circumciſion under the Law) ſo by Baptiſm under the Goſpel,
<note place="margin">Gen. 17.10.</note> which in the words premiſed is directed to.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As to its Form, In the Name of the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As to its Subject, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, All Nations.</p>
            <p n="3">3. As to its manner of Performance, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Baptizing them.</p>
            <p>Before I come to the Conſideration of the parts of the Text, I ſhall premiſe this Grand Enquiry, with its Solution.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Enq. How far Baptiſm is neceſſary as to Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and Church-memberſhip:</hi> which I ſhall Conſider, 1. Negatively. 2. Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitively.</p>
            <p n="1">1.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prop.</hi> 1.</note> I ſhall aſſert, that this Baptiſm of Water is not abſolutely neceſſary to Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, ſo as that it is impoſſible for a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to be ſaved who is not Baptized: which Propoſition I ſhall thus prove.</p>
            <p n="1">1.
<note place="margin">Gen. 17.10, 14.</note> Becauſe the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> under the Law (to whom Circumciſion was as ſtrictly enjoyned, as Baptiſm is, or can be
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:38078:6"/>to us) were Forty Years without its Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice; they being not Circumciſed all the time of their ſojourning in the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, leſt their ſoreneſs thereby occaſioned, might hinder them in their Travel to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Canaan,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joſh. 5.2, 3, 4, 5.</note> yet doubtleſs we dare not entertain thoughts that they who dyed in the Wilderneſs uncircumciſed were all Damned.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Salvation in no place of Scripture is annexed to Baptiſm, but to the Covenant, whoſe Tenor is not, Be Baptized, and thou ſhalt be Saved, but Believe, and thou ſhalt be Saved: Not was Chriſt given, that all who were Baptized, might have Eternal Life,
<note place="margin">John <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.16. Mark 16.16.</note> but that all who Believe on him. As for that place Objected againſt us, and Pleaded by the <hi>Anabaptiſts, Mark</hi> 16.16. it muſt either, if ſtrictly taken, include Infants as Believers, and ſo as ſubjects ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of Baptiſm; or elſe exclude them as Unbelievers, and render them as Perſons liable to Damnation, according to their own Argumentation; which if they evade by ſaying, they who are capable of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving, do believe, and are Baptized ſhall be ſaved.
<note place="margin">Order for Baptiſm of Riper Years.</note> I oppoſe to this the Practice of our Church, which requires actual Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Faith of all Perſons who are ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of doing it, and have been brought up unbaptized. And again, this Text
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:38078:7"/>when it reſpects Damnation, doth not mention Baptiſm, it ſaith not, He who is not Baptized ſhall be Damned; but he that believeth not. Salvation is annexed to Faith, and Damnation is the Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Unbelief. Baptiſm therefore is not abſolutely neceſſary to Salvation, nor its want abſolutely expoſing Souls to Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</p>
            <p n="3">3. This would be to tye God to means, and to make it in Mans Power to Save or Damn whom he pleaſed: For if it be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible any ſhould be ſaved without Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, then would it follow that it is Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm more than Gods free Grace that ſaves,
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.8.</note> and that it is in the Power of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter by Baptiſm to ſave whom he pleaſe, and by denying it, to damn whom he will Yea then, this Ordinance will be ſuppoſed to confer Grace, <hi>Ex Opere Operate,</hi> which Aſſertion detracts from Gods Glory, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agrees with Truth, and is injurious to Souls, who may be hereby brought to rely rather on a Creatures Baptiſm than their Creaton Mercy for Salvation.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Then all Children, and thoſe who dye unbaptized muſt be ſuppoſed not to appertain to Chriſt, nor to be ſaved by him, which to believe of all Infants is dreadful, whom I cannot implead of ſin in not being Baptized, being not capable
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:38078:7"/>of deſiring it. And though I cannot but think the Parent highly to Offend in ſlighting the Ordinance where it is to be obtained, yet cannot I ſuppoſe it to be by God imputed as a ſin to the Child ſo dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, for which he will damn it, which is the Genuine, though Diſmal Conſequence of that Poſition, That Baptiſm is abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely neceſſary to Salvation.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The Baptiſm contended for is but an outward ſign of that inward Grace which Entitles the Soul to Heaven,
<note place="margin">John 3.5.</note> and to which Glory is annexed; the ſign then cannot be ſo Eſſential, as that they who have received the things ſignified, and inward Grace, without Baptiſm ſhould ſtill be excluded Heaven becauſe they are not Baptized:
<note place="margin">Acts 10.47.</note> Which is as much as to aſſert, that though a Soul ſhould partake of all Chriſts Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits to be beſtowed on a Worthy Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicant, yet unleſs he actually Eat the Bread, and Drink the Wine, which are the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Elements in the Lords Supper, and Repreſentatives of thoſe inward Benefits, yet he could not be ſaved. A Theſis de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervedly to be exploded,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rubric</hi> 3. <hi>after Comm. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </note> as nullifying Chriſts Merits to Idolize External things: And our Church is clear againſt it.</p>
            <p n="6">6. By this Aſſertion it would follow, that many Thouſands of Chriſtians ſhall be Damned, who duly, and perhaps, more
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:38078:8"/>circumſpectly walk in Obedience to God than we, in, and amongſt the <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Pagans,</hi> who probably by Reaſon of their Perſecuted Condition, or the non-ſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a Church and Ordinances amongſt them, are, and ſo dye unbaptized. But how ſad this would be to a Chriſtians Eat. I leave every one to judge.</p>
            <p n="7">7. When ever Baptiſm is taken as ſo neceſſary to Salvation in Scripture, it hath reſpect to the Internal thing ſignified by it, ſo St.
<note place="margin">John 3.9.</note> 
               <hi>John</hi> hath chiefly reſpect to the Baptiſm of the Spirit, whereby the Soul is Regenerated and reduced to a ſtate of Grace (nor can the Baptiſm we contend about be there meant, this being not Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted till after our Saviours Reſurrection, which was ſome Years after theſe words were ſpoken by our Saviour.) And this Baptiſm of the Spirit is other where called A Baptiſm by Fire,
<note place="margin">Mat. 3.11.</note> denoting the cleanſing and purifying Nature of the Graces of the Holy Ghoſt, which purifies the Regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Soul from its Corruption, and burns up its droſſie Luſts. In compariſon of which Baptiſm St. <hi>John</hi> accounts his of Water (the Subject of our preſent Controverſie) ſo mean as only to have a Relation to it, as Precedaneous, not as Competitour. Again,
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.26, 27.</note> St. <hi>Paul</hi> joyns the Word of God with this Baptiſm, in order to the Purifying
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:38078:8"/>Chriſts Church; that acting on the Soul, and this terminating on the Body. And St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Aſſertion is clear,
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 3.21.</note> that it is not the Water Purifying the Fleſh, but the Anſwer of a good Conſcience towards God that ſaveth us: And indeed the Trope of uſing the ſign for the thing ſignified, is not unuſual in Scripture.</p>
            <p n="8">8. The All-wiſe God hath determined the Controverſie, in that He in divers places of his revealed Will, Aſſerts,
<note place="margin">Gal. 6.15 1 Cor. 7.19.</note> that neither Circumciſion nor Uncircumciſion avail any thing, but a New Creature. It is not the being an unbaptized Perſon that will expoſe any one to Condemnation; for there is not one Woe denounced againſt any as ſuch: Nor is there one Promiſe in all the Divine Writ Infallibly annexing Salvation to Baptiſm:
<note place="margin">2 Theſ. 1.8, 9. John 3.16.</note> All Threats of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery are to thoſe who believe not, and Obey not the Goſpel of Chriſt. And all Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of Eternal Mercies are to thoſe who by Faith cloſe with Chriſt, and live the life of Chriſtians. So that I dare not ſay, all who are Baptized ſhall be ſaved, and all who are not Baptized ſhall be damned. But I dare affirm, that whoſoever remain, and dyeth in unbelief ſhall be damned though he be Baptized. And whoever believes truly on Chriſt, and lives anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably to that Faith, though for ſome Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:38078:9"/>or other Cauſes he cannot be Baptized, he ſhall be ſaved.</p>
            <p>Whence will appear, That Baptiſm is not abſolutely Neceſſary to Salvation, ſo as that one cannot be ſaved without it.</p>
            <p>As I have hitherto endeavoured to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move the great Cenſure of the <hi>Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts</hi> of our being in no viſible ſalvable way (becauſe not Baptized after their Mode) by giving my Reaſons why Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm is not ſo abſolutely Neceſſary to Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. So I proceed to prove,</p>
            <p>That Baptiſm of Water is not abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely Neceſſary to Church-memberſhip,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prop.</hi> 2.</note> ſo as that they cannot be Members of Chriſts Church unleſs Baptized: Which will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear thus.</p>
            <p n="1">1.
<note place="margin">Wills <hi>againſt</hi> Danvers, p. 49.</note> There was ever a Church before Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm or Circumciſion were Adminiſtred: They being both External ſigns to be acted on viſible Profeſſors and Church-members in the Church of Chriſt, there is neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily preſuppoſed an exiſtence of a Church, containing Members to be Circumciſed or Baptized, and Perſons to perform theſe Offices. So that theſe ſigns are not the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>eſſe</hi> of a Church, or the Eſſential Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents of its viſibility. <hi>Noah, Seth,</hi> and thoſe Holy Patriarchs before the Flood, who
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:38078:9"/>Lived ſome hundreds of Years before the Inſtitution of Circumciſion,
<note place="margin">Gen. 17.24.</note> were doubtleſs Members of Gods Church. And <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> alſo doubtleſs before he was Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed, which was in the 99th. Year of his Age, and about the 2107 Year of the World, was a True Believer, and a Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the True Church. And if it be alledged, they were Members of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible Church, we may grant them a Memberſhip in the Viſible, from that known Axiom, <hi>Omne majus in ſe continet minus.</hi> Their being of the Inviſible Church being greater than their being Members of the Viſible Church: Yea, it is apparent the Promiſes were made to <hi>Abraham</hi> above Twenty Years before Circumciſion was In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted, which Promiſe he believed,
<note place="margin">Gen. 15.4, 5, 6, 7. Rom. 4.11.</note> and received Circumciſion as a Seal of his Faith, whence undeniably follows that Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion was not abſolutely Neceſſary to the Viſibility of Gods Church among the <hi>Jews.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Neither Circumciſion nor Baptiſm are abſolutely Neceſſary to the Being of a Church, becauſe a Viſible Church may be without them, and yet be a Church Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, as in the Inſtance of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> whom we proved to be forty Years toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Uncircumciſed in the Wilderneſs, and yet were they all that time the Viſible Church God had on the Earth.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:38078:10"/>
            <p n="3">3. If Perſons be not Church-members before Circumciſion or Baptiſm, and be ſo after, it will infer an Operation from the Ordinance not allowable, for then theſe being Circumciſed or Baptized would en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>title the Heathens to be Members of the Church of God and Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The <hi>Jews</hi> did firſt Proſelyte or Teach the Nations the Rudiments of their Law before they Circumciſed them, and ſo owned them to be received amongſt them. So that they were Proſelytes and Members as ſuch, of their Church before they were Publickly declared and owned to be ſo by Circumciſion. According to which, our Saviour Adviſeth his Diſciples in the Text,
<note place="margin">Mat. 28.19.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Going to Diſciple all Nations, Inſtruct them in the Principles of my Religion; and then being Diſciples, Baptize them: So that there is a Diſciple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and Viſible Church-memberſhip pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exiſtent to Baptiſm. And indeed the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing the word Diſciple implies none to be capable of Baptiſm who are not Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Chriſt, and Members of his Church, which alſo in due time Infants will be proved to be.</p>
            <p n="5">5. If Baptiſm be abſolutely Neceſſary to Church-memberſhip, that none belong to Chriſts Viſible Church but who are Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, what ſhall we think of that innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:38078:10"/>number of Profeſſing Chriſtians diſperſed over the Face of the whole Earth, and ſcattered amongſt Heathen People, whoſe Princes and Governours will not permit this or any other Chriſtian Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance to be Practiſed among them: Shall we unchurch theſe, or count them as Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens? What will then become of that Article of our Faith, The Belief of an Holy Catholick Church? Do not the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> herein imitate others, who while they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve a Catholick Church, confine it to their own Synagogues, not conſidering the Catholick Church of Chriſt comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive of all Chriſtian Profeſſors through the whole World, nor weighing the ſad Conſequents of denying Perſons to be Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly of this Church of Chriſt, making them thereby Viſible Members of Satans Kingdom, and expoſing thoſe Perſons in their Thoughts to Eternal Ruines, which Thoughts are too ſevere to entertain of thoſe who Profeſs the ſame God and Chriſt, but are not Baptized becauſe probably the Ordinances are not permitted in the Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories wherein they Reſide.</p>
            <p n="6">6. If Baptiſm give a Viſible Form to Church-memberſhip,
<note place="margin">Wills <hi>againſt</hi> Danvers. p. 50, 51, 52.</note> then muſt it be often repeated, even as often as any Perſon is Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated, or elſe Baptiſm is nullified, for it being the Chriſtian Practice of the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:38078:11"/>Apoſtles and their Succeſſors even to our Ages,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 5.4, 5.</note> to exclude their Aſſemblies, and Excommunicate Perſons, which was termed a giving ſuch over to Satan who were guilty of ſcandalous Offences,
<note place="margin">2 Theſ. 3.6. Mat. 18.17.</note> till by their Humiliation they had Evidenced their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and ſo were received again into their Aſſemblies. If that Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion can Exclude the Perſon from being a Member of the Church (as it ever did) then it nullifies Baptiſm, or elſe Baptiſm is not Eſſential to the Form of Viſible Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memberſhip, becauſe it would then follow, that the Perſon even Excommunicated, is ſtill a Member of the Viſible Church, which is a contradictory Soleciſm, or elſe that his Baptiſm is nulled, and then muſt Rationally be repeated at his Reception into the Church again; and ſo as often as any being guilty of a Crime, is for it Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated, and afterwards received into the Church again, ſo often muſt he be re-baptized,
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.5.</note> which is oppoſite to the Scriptures Aſſertion of but <hi>One Baptiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus have I endeavoured to prove Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm contended for, to be not ſo abſolutely Neceſſary to Salvation or Church-mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berſhip, as that none can be ſaved, or be of Chriſts Church unleſs they be Baptized, to remove the unchriſtian Cenſures the <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts</hi> have of us. But</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:38078:11"/>
            <p>Leſt on the other ſide I ſhould detract from the Ordinance and its due worth by rendring its uſe needleſs.</p>
            <p>I proceed to prove that the Practice of Baptiſm is very Neceſſary as an Ordinance of Chriſt in any Church of his where it may be had,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prop.</hi> 3.</note> and that the ſlighters and contemners of it are really Culpable. Which I prove thus.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Chriſt hath Commanded its Perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance in his Churches under the Goſpel to the end of the World:
<note place="margin">Mat. 28.19.</note> And all his Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances and Commands ought by us to be Obſerved.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Chriſt himſelf was ſubject to it,
<note place="margin">Mat. 3.16. Acts 10.47.</note> and therefore none can pretend to be above it, though they have already received the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Apoſtles Practiſed it.
<note place="margin">Mat. 3.1.</note> St. <hi>John</hi> from hence was called the Baptiſt. And whenever the Goſpel was Preached to the <hi>Gentiles</hi> and unconverted <hi>Jews,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 10.48. Acts 2.38, 41. Acts 16.31, 32. Acts 16.15. 1 Cor. 1.16.</note> and received by them. The General way whereby the Apoſtles owned the Converts was Baptiſm; and we find not only ſingle Perſons, but whole Families Baptized.</p>
            <p n="4">4. It is a Seal of the Covenant of Grace which when made to &amp; received by <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> he alſo received Circumciſion as a Seal of it. And Baptiſm ſucceeding Circumciſion
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:38078:12"/>denotes probably our greater Priviledges by Chriſt than the <hi>Jews</hi> had before Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Rom. 4.11.</note> who was of the one Sex, and derived our Nature from the other by this Sacrament admitting both Sexes to equal Priviledges, that of Circumciſion only belonging to the Males. And Baptiſm may as ſignificantly be a Seal of the Covenant of Grace, as Circumciſion,
<note place="margin">Acts 2.38. Gal. 3.27. Rom. 6.3, 4, &amp;c.</note> the Perſon Baptized being ſaid to put on Chriſt, which Phraſe implies his being Inveſted with a Right to the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges of Chriſtians, and the Benefits of Chriſt. And thus it is of great Uſe.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Many of the Converts to Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity have ſoon after their being Baptized, received the Holy Ghoſt,
<note place="margin">Acts 8.16, 17.</note> to whoſe Baptiſm this ſeems precedaneous and preparatory. And Gods uſual way of working in an Eſtabliſhed Church and Ordinances, Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm being a Publick Sign manifeſting the Perſons Baptized to be Publickly owned as Members of Chriſt, and Children of God, to which this Spirit of Adoption is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed.
<note place="margin">Gal. 4.4, 6, 7.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. This ſerves as a diſtinguiſhing Mark in a ſettled Church to know Profeſſors of Chriſtianity from <hi>Jews, Turks,</hi> and <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens,</hi> ſo that all who would manifeſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be of Chriſts Church, ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to partake of, and ſubmit to this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of Baptiſm. And all Chriſtian
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:38078:12"/>Parents ought to deſire it for their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, ſince none beneath Heaven can be above Gods Ordinances. Chriſt, though without ſin, and the Converts who had received the Holy Ghoſt, we have premi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to have ſubmitted to Baptiſm,
<note place="margin">Rom. 6.</note> the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Refuſal and Contempt of which where in an Eſtabliſh'd Church it may be had, is a Contempt of Chriſt and his Precepts, and as much as lyeth in us, a depriving of our ſelves or Children of the Benefits of the Covenant of Grace, and a reducing us into a ſtate of Heatheniſm, or at beſt an unwillingneſs to be owned as Chriſtians.</p>
            <p n="7">7. It ſerves as an Oath and Obligation on Souls to be, and continue Chriſts Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Souldier and Servant to our Lives end. Our Life is often in Scripture called a war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare, wherein we are engaged to fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the World, Fleſh, and Devil, to engage us againſt whom, the Lord of Hoſts, the chief General of the Field, and Chriſt the Captain of our Salvation, Liſt all their Souldiers, the Members of the Church Militant here on Earth, to Fight under their Banner, till they have their Writs of Eaſe by Death, and have their Quarters removed from the Church-Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant on Earth to the Church Triumphant in Heaven: Into which Militia this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance is the Publick way of our Admiſſion,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:38078:13"/>and is as it were our Matriculation, or ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the Oath of Allegiance to our God,
<note place="margin">Col. 2.6, 7.</note> thereby diſcriminating us from Rebels and Traytors, and engaging our Fidelity to our Lives end.</p>
            <p n="8">8. The uncircumciſed Child was to be cut off from <hi>Iſrael,</hi> which Puniſhment reſpects either its Excluſion from the Church of Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Gen. 17.14.</note> and ſo its cutting off from the <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God: Or elſe a puniſhing of the Child by Death, and ſo taking it away from among the People. Or, Laſtly, it ſignifies an Eternal Excluding it from Heaven, and a cutting it off for ever from Gods People and their Portion. Now, though probably the Puniſhment in the Text on the Uncircumciſed Child may not denote its being thereby Miſerable to Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, for what it could not help: Yet to engage the Parents care to obſerve the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant and Gods Ordinances in having the Child Circumciſed, it might be puniſhed both the other ways, which could not but be a great trouble to the Parent, whoſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſneſs or neglect of the Ordinance might cauſe himſelf in his Child to be Puniſhed, either with his Childs Death, or if it Lived, by its being eſteemed not of the Church of God, but to be looked on as an Heathen. And ſo under the Goſpel, although the Child ſhall not probably for the want of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:38078:13"/>Baptiſm (it being guilty of no contempt of it) ſuffer Eternally;
<note place="margin">Walkers <hi>Modeſt Plea. p.</hi> 147.</note> yet may the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent juſtly fear to be ſeverely Puniſhed for ſlighting and contemning the Sacred Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of God and Chriſt, commanded to be Obſerved.</p>
            <p>Thus are the Enquiries premiſed conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, and the Neceſſity of Baptiſm ſtated.</p>
            <p>I proceed more cloſely to adhere to the Expoſition of the Parts of the Text.
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Part of Text.</hi> 1. <hi>Form.</hi>
               </note> Wherein we Obſerved,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Form or Eſſence of Baptiſm. <hi>Baptizing them in the Name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> And I eſteem this the Form or Eſſence of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, becauſe though there be a ſubject ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of Baptiſm, and Water be uſed to Baptize, yet is the Baptiſm Null unleſs in the Name of the Trinity, according to Chriſts Commiſſion in the Text, which is never Repealed in any part of the New Teſtament.</p>
            <p>As for the Baptizing Perſons into the Name of Chriſt mentioned ſometimes,
<note place="margin">Acts 2.38. Acts 8.16.</note> that doth not derogate from Chriſts Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion in the Text, thoſe places not rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to the manner of Adminiſtring the Ordinance, but to the end of Baptiſm, for the <hi>Jews,</hi> who were pricked in their hearts for the Crucifying of Chriſt (whom St.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:38078:14"/>
               <hi>Peter</hi> had proved to be the <hi>Meſſiah</hi>) and enquired what they ſhould do to be ſaved. The Apoſtle Exhorts them to believe on a Crucified Saviour, and to be Baptized in,
<note place="margin">Acts 4.12. Acts 10.48.</note> or into his Name, as a Token of their owning him as their <hi>Meſſiah</hi> and Saviour, without whom no Salvation was attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. And thoſe other places mentioning the Baptizing in the Name of the Lord, or in the Name of Chriſt, have the like reſpect, denoting the Converted <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles,</hi> being by Baptiſm received into the Name or Religion of Chriſt. And they do not in the leaſt infringe our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours Commiſſion of Baptizing in the Name of the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt. And therefore the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> ſeem to be blame-worthy,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Article</hi> 11. 1660 <hi>given to our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent King</hi>
               </note> who in their Printed Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples give Order indifferently to Baptize in the Name of the Trinity, or in the Name of Chriſt alone, which Practice is directly contrary to this Precept of our Saviour, by which the Perſon to be Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized was Baptized <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> into the Name, Profeſſion, and Service of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Trinity. The Acknowledgment of the ever Bleſſed Trinity, and the Grounds of the Souls hope of enjoying all the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes and Benefits of Chriſts Death, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation and Grace being thereby Rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied and Scaled to the Soul,
<note place="margin">Epl. eſ. 5.1.</note> who is alſo thus
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:38078:14"/>engaged to act as a Child of God,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 6.18, 19, 20. Rom. 6.11.</note> a Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Chriſt, and a Temple of the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>The Form or Eſſence of Baptiſm being Proved,
<note place="margin">2. <hi>Part of Text. Subject</hi>
               </note> we come to conſider the Subject of Baptiſm, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>all Nations;</hi> which in Scripture is ſpoken either,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Excluſively as to the <hi>Jews,</hi> and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſively only of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> who were through Chriſt to be received into the Church of God,
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.2, 12, 13, 19.</note> and be made Members of Chriſt, were admitted to partake of the Benefits of a ſtate of Grace through Chriſt, and by him alſo were made Heirs of Glory. So that through Chriſt they were admitted to equal Priviledges with the <hi>Jews,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 2.3, 7, 9. Acts 10.34, 35, 49.</note> which thing, though it cauſed an aſtoniſhment to the <hi>Jews,</hi> yet was in Remarkable Eviden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces verified; ſo that now all the ends of the Earth have ſeen the Salvation of God, who is become God of the <hi>Gentile</hi> as well as <hi>Jew,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 3.29.</note> and without Reſpect of Perſons hath Reſpect to all thoſe, whether <hi>Jews</hi> or <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles,</hi> who truly ſerve him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Incluſively of the <hi>Jews</hi> alſo, for that Chriſt who was ſo long before his mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation Promiſed as a <hi>Meſſiah</hi> and Saviour to the loſt ſheep of the Houſe of <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mar. 10.5, 6.</note> would not, when manifeſted, exclude them, but being to Collect a Church to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:38078:15"/>himſelf,
<note place="margin">Mark 16 16. Acts 26.17, 18. Acts 13.46, 47. Acts 28.28.</note> he did Perſonally, and by his Apoſtles firſt promulgate the Goſpel to the <hi>Jews,</hi> and they rejecting it, he Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned his Apoſtles to go to the <hi>Gentiles</hi> as well as <hi>Jews,</hi> who diſcharging their Office, prevailed with great Numbers of both to accept of Chriſt; to ſhew the equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of Chriſts proceedings, and the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Gods Mercy to both <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile,</hi> that of both all and every one who will believe on him ſhould be ſaved by him.</p>
            <p>And in this Incluſive ſenſe, as compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending both <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Gentile,</hi> even all Nations, theſe words, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, are to be taken, and accordingly (both <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Gentile</hi> being to be Diſcipled to Chriſt) our ever Bleſſed Saviour ſeems to adapt his Commiſſion ſuitably to the Practice of the <hi>Jews</hi> in their gathering of their Church; for whereas they obſerved three things therein, ſo our Saviour in the Text by three words ſeems to obſerve this Method in gathering his Goſpel-Church. For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Jews</hi> did firſt Proſelyte the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, by acquainting them with the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diments of their Law, and thereby in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing them <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to come over from Heatheniſm to the <hi>Jews</hi> Religion, and to embrace that. So Chriſt Commands his Diſciples, that they going to Conſtitute a
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:38078:15"/>Church out of all Nations, ſhould firſt endeavour <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to Diſciple them by Preaching to both <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> the verity of Chriſt manifeſted in the Fleſh, the Reality of his Death and Reſurrection, the Rationality of all thoſe things which the Scriptures relate to be done or ſuffered by Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Acts 2.37. Acts 16.31. Iſai 53.</note> and the Neceſſity of all Perſons adhering to this Crucified Chriſt as their Saviour; how that the ſufferings of Chriſt were fore-told concerning the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> to the <hi>Jews,</hi> and the <hi>Gentiles</hi> Sacrifices might re-mind them of their Thoughts, ſin could not be expiated but by Death; and thus the Occaſion of ſtumbling at, or deriding of the Goſpel of Chriſt being removed from <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Gentile,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 1.16. 1 Cor. 1.23, 24. Mat. 18.11.</note> the Apoſtles urged a cloſure with Chriſt by the free and full Mercies tendered through him to all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning ſinners, and the Grand Priviledges of ſuch a ſtate of Grace, together with the exceeding weight of Glory reſerved in Heaven for Chriſts People.
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 6.1.</note> And thus pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>united with many (through Gods co-work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) to become Chriſts Diſciples.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As the <hi>Jews</hi> did by Gods Command Circumciſe, ſo the Diſciples did by Chriſts Order Baptize the Proſelyte or Convert, and ſo received him as one of the Church.
<note place="margin">Gen. 17.12, 13.</note> And as the <hi>Jews</hi> did not only Circumciſe the Aged Proſelyte, but all his Children,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:38078:16"/>ſo Chriſt Commands the Diſcipled Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to be Baptized; nor did he only ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit as his Diſciples the Aged and Adult Perſons,
<note place="margin">Mark 10 13. Mat. 19.15. Luk. 18.15.</note> but <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, little Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and Infants <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to come unto him, or become his Proſelytes, as the very import of the words denote, which Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelytiſm or Diſcipleſhip, renders them ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of Baptiſm,
<note place="margin">Acts 2.38.</note> as will in due time be more fully proved. And indeed the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles having Diſcipled or Converted the Maſter or Parent of a Family, we frequently find them Baptizing the whole Family,
<note place="margin">Acts 16.15, 31.</note> in which ſeveral Families it may as Reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly be preſumed there were ſome Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, as it can be confidently denyed.</p>
            <p>And as for the change of the mode of Admiſſion of Proſelytes under the Law, and of Converts under the Goſpel into the Church of God and Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Euxtorf. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. <hi>de Sin. Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dai.</hi> Godwin. <hi>Awiq. of Proſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tes Dr.</hi> Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond's <hi>Query of Infant Bap. Mr.</hi> Wal ker's <hi>Plea, p.</hi> 9.</note> from Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion to Baptiſm, it may probably appear rather a Sacramental Confirmation of an Ancient Cuſtom, than an Innovation of a New Rite: For if Learned Authors may be Credited, or their Citations believed, the Practice of Baptizing Proſelytes was uſed by the <hi>Jews,</hi> who thereby as by one means received them into their Church; yea, as to Females it was the chief, if not only way of their Admiſſion. Which waſhing or Baptiſin of the Proſelyte Scripture ſeems
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:38078:16"/>to give us ſome Reaſon to think the <hi>Jews</hi> expected to be by the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> made Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental,
<note place="margin">Wills <hi>againſt</hi> Danvers, <hi>p.</hi> 7. John 1.25, 28.</note> elſe what may their Enquiry of St. <hi>John</hi> mean? when they asked him why he Baptized if he was not the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> that ſhould come? Rather ſcrupling his Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to Baptize, than in the leaſt Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oning the Lawfulneſs of the Ordinance: Which Enquiry certainly ſounds as much as a Tacite acknowledgment of their Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſing it, though not as a Sacrament till the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> had confirmed it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>Jews</hi> having Circumciſed their Proſelytes, brought them up in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Law. And our Saviour ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Ordered his Diſciples to Diſciple all Nations, Baptizing them, doth afterward command their Teaching, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Teaching them to Obſerve all things which he had Commanded,
<note place="margin">Mat. 18.20.</note> to Edifie them in the Holy Faith, in which Work he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed himſelf their co-worker to the Worlds end.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Jews</hi> did firſt Teach, and then Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſe their Proſelytes, but they firſt Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed, and then Taught the Children of thoſe Proſelytes: And ſo all Nations are firſt Taught to bring them to a ſtate of Diſcipleſhip before Baptiſm: But the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of ſuch Converts and Diſciples are firſt Baptized, and then Taught, and that
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:38078:17"/>on good Warrant, which I endeavour to prove thus.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="arguments">
            <head>Arguments for Infant Baptiſm.</head>
            <div n="1" type="argument">
               <head>ARGUMENT I.</head>
               <p>IF our Chriſtian Priviledges be as great as the <hi>Jews</hi> were, then our Children are rightly Baptized. But our Chriſtian Priviledges are as great as the <hi>Jews</hi> were, therefore our Children are rightly Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized.</p>
               <p>In this Hypothetical Argument the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor</hi> is to be proved; and I ſhall endeavour to manifeſt that our Chriſtian Priviledges are as great as the <hi>Jews</hi> were, which being proved, I ſhall prove the conſequence thence following, that our Chriſtian Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges being as great as the <hi>Jews</hi> were, our Children are rightly Baptized.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Our Chriſtian Priviledges are as great as the Jews were, as will thus appear.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:38078:17"/>
               <p n="1">1. The ſame Covenant of Grace made through Chriſt with the <hi>Jews</hi> is alſo made with the <hi>Gentiles,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 2.39. Epheſ. 2.13, 19. Gen. 17.10.</note> whereby God promiſeth himſelf to be the God of his People, and of their Seed: It is called a Covenant of Grace, to the full extent of which, <hi>Gentiles</hi> as well as <hi>Jews</hi> are now through Chriſt admitted.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Elſe our Condition is worſe ſince Chriſt than the <hi>Jews</hi> ſtate was before Chriſt, nor is Chriſt then a Mediator of a better Covenant, as he is ſaid to be in Scripture.
<note place="margin">Heb. 8.6.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Scripture Witneſſeth the <hi>Gentiles</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing received to the ſame and equal Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges with the <hi>Jews,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 11. Rom. 3.29. Epheſ. 2.13, 19.</note> and that now both are Co-heirs through Chriſt of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Elſe could we ſcarce perſwade a <hi>Jew</hi> to become a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> who might well Plead againſt his Converſion, the Privation of thoſe Priviledges he was Inveſted with by the Law, whereby his Child as well as himſelf was within the Covenant with God, and admitted by God to the Seal of the Covenant, while he remains a <hi>Jew.</hi> But if by his eſpouſing Chriſtianity he muſt part with this Priviledge, and exclude his Child the Covenant, and cannot ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit it to Baptiſm, the Seal of it, now un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Goſpel, few <hi>Jews</hi> would become <hi>Chriſtians.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:38078:18"/>
               <p>Then ſurely they are to blame who ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe Chriſtians Priviledges ſince Chriſt are not as great as the <hi>Jews</hi> were before Chriſt. Which being granted, Baptiſm of our Children muſt follow. Therefore,</p>
               <p n="2">2. If our Chriſtian Priviledges being as great as the <hi>Jews</hi> were, our Children are rightly Baptized, as will appear by theſe Reaſons.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Children of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lytes were with their Proſelyted Parents Circumciſed, to which Baptiſm ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Church, the Children of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples and Profeſſors of Chriſtianity ought to be Baptized, as will be farther mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted from my next Argument drawn from Circumciſion.</p>
               <p n="2">2. None were Excluded the Covenant of Grace among the <hi>Jews,</hi> or amongſt Chriſtians, or are uncapable of its Seal, Circumciſion or Baptiſm,
<note place="margin">Rom. 11.20, 21.</note> but actual Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believers; of which Crime Children of <hi>Jews</hi> or <hi>Chriſtians</hi> could not, nor can be impleaded.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Believing <hi>Jews</hi> and their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren kept their Priviledges after their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion to Chriſtianity that they enjoyed before:
<note place="margin">Acts 2.39. Rom. 11. <hi>at large.</hi>
                  </note> And therefore their Children might as well be Baptized after their Parents be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came Chriſtians, as they might have been Circumciſed before, or elſe their Priviledges
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:38078:18"/>by Converſion were infringed, and their caſe worſe than before, becauſe,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Their Children were before their Converſion to Chriſtianity, within the Covenant, and had Right to, and were admitted to the Seal of it, but now by the Parents eſpouſing Chriſtianity, the Child would be debarred the Seal, which implies its Excluſion from the Covenant.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They and their Children were eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the People of God before their Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to Chriſt; but ſince, though the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents were received as Converted Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, yet the Children would but be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted as Heathens till they became Men, or were able to give an Account of their Faith, and ſo be Baptized.</p>
               <p n="3">3. This would leave the Converted <hi>Jew</hi> but ſmall grounds for the hopes of his Childrens Salvation, if they dyed Young; becauſe they would not be looked on as Members of Chriſts Church,
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.12.</note> within the Covenant of God, or to have Right to its Promiſes.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The ſame Promiſes made to the <hi>Jews</hi> are alſo made to the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> which Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes include their Seed or Children as well as themſelves.
<note place="margin">Acts 2.39.</note> The Promiſe was to the <hi>Jews</hi> who were near, and to their Seed, and to the <hi>Gentiles</hi> who were afar off, and to as many as the Lord our God ſhould
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:38078:19"/>call, and to their Seed, which Promiſe gives our Children Right to Baptiſm as well as it did the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Children to Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The Children of the <hi>Jews</hi> as well as the Aged, in Order to their Publick Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception into the Church of God, were Circumciſed; therefore the Children of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> Converted together with the <hi>Jews</hi> to Chriſtianity may juſtly have Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, it being the Sacrament of Admiſſion into Chriſts Church under the Goſpel, as Circumciſion was under the Law. And that the former is true, to wit, that the Children with the Parent were under the Law Circumciſed, the Scripture is ſo plain, that none will deny it; and that our Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren then may be, yea, ought to be Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, muſt be granted from a Conceſſion of our Priviledges being as great as the <hi>Jews.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But this will ſtill be clearer in my next Argument.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="argument">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:38078:19"/>
               <head>ARGUMENT II. <hi>Thoſe who were Circumciſed under the Law may be Baptized under the Goſpel. But Children were Circumciſed under the Law, therefore Children may be Baptized under the Goſpel.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis Argument is Categorical, whoſe Concluſion cannot be denyed if the Premiſſes be granted, I ſhall therefore prove each Propoſition.</p>
               <p>The Minor Propoſition,
<note place="margin">Maour preved.</note> That Children were Circumciſed under the Law is ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly true, relying on the expreſs Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts and Practice of God and his People,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.10, 11, 12.</note> that I ſuppoſe it will not be denyed.</p>
               <p>And the truth of the Major Propoſition I ſhall endeavour to demonſtrate theſe two ways:
<list>
                     <item>1. By Arguments for it.</item>
                     <item>2. Solving Objections againſt it.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. I ſhall prove by Arguments, That thoſe who were Circumciſed under the Law may be Baptized under the Goſpel.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Baptiſm ſucceeded Circumciſion, and as that was the Sacrament of Admiſſion into the Church under the Law, ſo is this
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:38078:20"/>under the Goſpel,
<note place="margin">Col. 2.11, 12.</note> having this Priviledge above the other, that it may be Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred to either Male or Female,
<note place="margin">Mat. 28.29.</note> and may be performed to all Nations, <hi>Gentile</hi> as well as <hi>Jew.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Our Children are now as capable of being Baptized as the Children of the <hi>Jews</hi> were then of being Circumciſed at Eight days old: Ours underſtand the ends of Baptiſm as much as theirs did the ends of Circumciſion; and ours are as capable of Teſtifying their Converſion to Chriſtianity, as the Proſelyted <hi>Jews</hi> Children were to Evidence their being Proſelyted; nor can any Objection be framed againſt our Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens Capability of Baptiſm, but it is equally Valid againſt their Childrens being capable of Circumciſion.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Precept of God for the receiving Parent and Child into Covenant,
<note place="margin">Gen. 17. Acts 2.39.</note> ſtands unrepealed to this day, nor can the leaſt jota be produced to forbid Children of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing Chriſtians Baptiſm, or that Chriſt, who was the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> and Saviour of both <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Gentile</hi> (and had admitted the Children of the <hi>Jews</hi> all along to the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Seal of Circumciſion as a Diagnoſtick of their being his People) would, or did exclude them in his Goſpel Diſpenſation from Baptiſm. But many Reaſons may be offered why their Baptizing is not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:38078:20"/>Commanded, which I ſhall propoſe in due time. At preſent let us conſider ſince there is no reſtraint or countermand of the Ancient <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Practice of receiving Children to Circumciſion. And ſince Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm is an Ordinance ſucceeding it, it ſeems to me apparent, that they who were Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed may be Baptized.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Chriſt is propoſed as a Mediator of a better Covenant, not of a worſe,
<note place="margin">Heb. 8.6.</note> founded on better, not on leſs Promiſes; enlarging, not infringing his Peoples Priviledges, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing ſtill God, a God in Covenant with his People and their Seed, and then doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs this great Priviledge is not Repealed, but Children, the Seed of his People, may Lawfully be Baptized, as being ſtill within the Covenant of Grace, whereof Baptiſm under his Goſpel-diſpenſation is a Seal: Elſe our Children have no greater Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge by being Born of Chriſtians, than the Children of <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Pagans, Jews</hi> and <hi>Infidels</hi> enjoy.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Expreſs Scripture avers the Incluſion of Believers Seed with themſelves in the Covenant. Nor can the word <hi>Calling,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 2.37, 38, 39.</note> in the place Cited, be reſtrained to the word Seed, as if they only were in Covenant with God (of the Seed of the Righteous) whom God called and Converted, which would be no other Priviledge than the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:38078:21"/>Heathens may enjoy, who when Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted are admitted into Covenant. But the word, I preſume, may well be referred to the preſent Believer, who is called and his Seed, and of Gods owning all Believers, whom in future Ages he ſhould call, and their Seeds. So that if the Children of us, as well as the <hi>Jews</hi> be in Covenant with God, and Baptiſm now, as well as Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion then, be a Seal of the Covenant, to be Adminiſtred to all in the Covenant, then certainly it muſt follow that Children of the <hi>Jews,</hi> as in Covenant with God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing admitted to its Seal, Circumciſion, the Children of Chriſtians being equally in Covenant, may and ought to be admitted to its Seal, which now is Baptiſm.</p>
               <p>Thus is the Major Propoſition proved, and thoſe who were Circumcifed under the Law, manifeſted to have a Right to Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm under the Goſpel. I proceed,</p>
               <p n="2">2. To Receive and Anſwer the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections I have met with againſt this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> 1. They Object, The Covenant then made, was a Carnal Covenant, but this through Chriſt is a Spiritual Covenant, and therefore though Infants may be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of one, yet not of the other, till Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generated and become Believers.</p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:38078:21"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. The Covenant then made was a Covenant of Grace, permanent to the Worlds end,
<note place="margin">Gen. 17.10, 13.</note> made through Chriſt the Promiſed Seed, and is the ſame Covenant we are now admitted to, nor ſhall it ever be Repealed while Chriſt hath a People on Earth. Which thus appears.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It was made with <hi>Abraham,</hi> who in Scripture is often called the Father of the Faithful,
<note place="margin">Rom. 4.11.</note> and it was made with him as a Believer: Therefore it was a Covenant of Grace.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It was made through Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Gen. 17.7.</note> in whom all the Families of the Earth ſhould be Bleſſed, who was that Promiſed Seed, to proceed from <hi>Abraham.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. It is often called an Everlaſting Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, and therefore this Covenant of Grace hath been often in ſucceeding Ages urged to God by his People to re-mind him of his Promiſes made to <hi>Abraham.</hi> And God alſo in divers Ages hath declared himſelf to his People by the Title of the God of <hi>Abraham.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. The Tenor of that Covenant is the ſame with ours now,
<note place="margin">Gal. 3. <hi>latter end.</hi> Heb. 11.</note> that God will be a God of his People and their Seed, and that they who believe on him, ſhall be accepted by him.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Scripture Atteſts Circumciſion to have been to <hi>Abraham</hi> a Seal of the Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:38078:22"/>of Faith,
<note place="margin">Rom. 4.1.</note> which implies that Covenant made with <hi>Abraham</hi> to have been a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> 2. But they Object again, That the Seed here in the Covenant, and that had Right to Circumciſion, the Seal of it, was a Spiritual Seed, and therefore Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers ought only to be Baptized. To which I Anſwer,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. The Seed in the Covenant de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noted not only the Spiritual Seed, but all the Natural Seed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> all proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from his Loyns,
<note place="margin">Gen. 17.23, 13, 14.</note> 
                  <hi>Iſhmael</hi> as well as <hi>Iſaac</hi> was Circumciſed, and every Male Child Born of all the Strangers that were Proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyted to the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Religion.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Natural Seed as Men belonged to the Viſible Church of God, and ſo were in a Capacity to receive that Seal and Mark diſtinguiſhing them from the <hi>Gentiles</hi> and <hi>Heathens,</hi> which was only an Ordinance belonging to a Viſible Church, of which Men might Judge.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Uncircumciſed were denyed many Common Priviledges; yea, it was a Scandal for the <hi>Jews</hi> to Aſſociate with them, or to joyn in Affinity with them, which Priviledges could not be granted only to the Spiritual Seed,
<note place="margin">Gen. 34.14.</note> becauſe it would be much injurious to Humane Society, nor indeed could their Spiritual ſtate, or their
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:38078:22"/>being the Spiritual Seed of <hi>Abraham</hi> come under Mans Cognizance.</p>
               <p n="4">4. This would crect Men as Judges of our Hearts and Spirituality, which cannot be diſcerned by any Mortal Eye,
<note place="margin">Jer. 17.9, 10. 2 Tim. 2.19.</note> but is only known to that Immortal God, who tryeth the Heart, whence proceeds that diſtinction of an Inviſible Church, conſiſting of true Believers only, whom God alone knows, and of a Viſible Church, containing all Chriſtian Profeſſors, whoſe Members are diſcernable by Men.</p>
               <p n="5">5. If Baptiſm or Circumciſion be only applicable to the Spiritual Seed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> true Believers, the Ordinances would ſoon be null as to their Adminiſtration, becauſe we know not then whom to Baptize, not dare we ſay, this Man, or Child, is a true Believer, and one of the Spiritual Seed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and the other is not; and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably may thus admit thoſe to the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances who are Hypocrites, while we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject thoſe who are true Believers.
<note place="margin">Cen. 17.22. Acts 8.13, 18, 23.</note> There have been Perſons Baptized and Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed, who yet doubtleſs were not of the Spiritual Seed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> witneſs the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of <hi>Iſhmael</hi> and <hi>Simon Magus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. The Children the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> refuſe, may be the Spiritual Seed of <hi>Abraham</hi> for ought they or we know. <hi>Jeremiah</hi> and St. <hi>John</hi> were Sanctified from the Womb, and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:38078:23"/>known by God to be his before they were Born, and ſo before they could be under Mans Cognizance. And who dare ſay, that the Children they refuſe are not par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of the Holy Ghoſt, or by God ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted as Believers? What would be the Reſult of ſuch Expreſſions? Should thoſe dye in their Infancy, who dare ſay they are Damned? Nay, the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> grant them a Capability of Salvation, and ſay, all Children dying Children ſhall be ſaved; and then ſurely they eſteem them the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Seed of <hi>Abraham:</hi> And if ſo (the Children not Acting any thing to render them uncapable) they might by their own Arguings be Subjects fit to be Baptized.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="argument">
               <head>ARGUMENT III. <hi>Thoſe who are within the Covenant of Grace may be Baptized. But Children are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Covenant of Grace. Therefore they may be Baptized.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE Major of this Argument is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified, in that Baptiſm is now the Seal of the Covenant between God and his People, as Circumciſion was under the Law; and therefore thoſe who are thus in
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:38078:23"/>Covenant with God,
<note place="margin">Col. 2.11, 12.</note> may be admitted to the Participation of its Seal as thoſe were.</p>
               <p>The Minor, That Children are within the Covenant of Grace, is thus undeniably confirmed.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Gods Grace is Univerſal, appertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Children as well as Adult Perſons; Chriſt dyed for them as well as Men and Women, and they partake of his Benefits as well as the other, and ſhall be ſaved hereafter as well as grown Perſons.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Children were ever in the Covenant with God, and never rejected or caſt out by Chriſt, nor that Covenant Repealed, and we have already proved the Covenant including Children as well as Parents to be a Covenant of Grace, and ſo everlaſting: Therefore Children are ſtill in the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace.</p>
               <p n="3">3. They never Excluded themſelves,
<note place="margin">Rom. 11.20.</note> becauſe not actual Unbelievers, and none but ſuch were rejected, therefore they are ſtill in the Covenant.</p>
               <p n="4">4. They have the Promiſes of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant belonging to them,
<note place="margin">Acts 2.37, 38, 39.</note> and renewed to them with their Converted Parents, which would not be unleſs Chriſt ſtill comprehended them as well as their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents within the Covenant.</p>
               <p n="5">5. They are termed Holy, though Born but of one Believing Parent. And this
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:38078:24"/>Holineſs cannot be underſtood of Legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy or Lawfulneſs of Birth (as I have met with the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> Gloſſing) as if the Child by being Born of one Believing Parent,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 7.14.</note> was thereby no Baſtard: For this would have been no Obligation on the Unbelieving Husband or Wife to Co-habit with the Believer, it being a Priviledge common to all Unbelievers as well as them to have the Children Born in Lawful Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock to be eſteemed Lawful. But this Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs in the Text muſt be underſtood of a foederal or Covenant Holineſs, whereby the Children would be by God eſteemed as Holy, and in Covenant with him: They being as Children not yet capable of acting Holineſs.</p>
               <p n="6">6. If Children were in Covenant before Chriſt, and are rejected ſince Chriſt, then would follow,</p>
               <p n="1">1. That we loſe and gain not Priviledges by the Incarnation and Death of our ever Bleſſed Saviour,
<note place="margin">Heb. 8.6. Epheſ. 2.12, 13.</note> it being no better, but a worſe ſtate which excludes Thouſands, even all Children, though of Believing Parents, the Covenant of Grace, which did include them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Then is there no difference between the Children of Believers and the Children of <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Infidels,</hi> who when at Are, and are Converted, may be eſteemed
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:38078:24"/>Chriſtians, and be Baptized, and outs can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be Baptized according to their Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion before.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Then cannot we propoſe an encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raging Motive to a <hi>Jew</hi> to become a <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian,</hi> whereby his Child, as yet within the Covenant, would be excluded.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Then can we have no good Viſible grounds for the hopes of our Childrens Salvation. If they be out of the Covenant of Grace, they are debarred of the Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits of Chriſt, which I ſuppoſe will ſeem harſh to any conſiderate Chriſtian. Nor can I ſee how the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> can think all Children ſhall be ſaved, unleſs they be within the Covenant of Grace; and if they ſo think, I humbly ſuppoſe they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deny Baptiſm to them, which is the Seal of the Covenant.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="argument">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:38078:25"/>
               <head>ARGUMENT IV. <hi>Thoſe who have Right to the Bleſſings of the Covenant, have Right to Baptiſm. But Children have Right to the Bleſſings of the Covenant, Therefore they have Right to Baptiſm.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Major. </seg>
                  </label> THAT Propoſition of their having Right to Baptiſm, who have Right to the Bleſſings of the Covenant, relyeth on theſe Reaſons,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Circumciſion was, and Baptiſm is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted as a Seal of the Covenant of Grace, confirming to the receiver of it Gods Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception of his Soul into a ſtate of Grace and Favour, and a ratifying the Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes through Chriſt made, that if the Soul walked anſwerably to the Covenant of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Gods Servant,
<note place="margin">Rom. 4.11.</note> God would make good his part, in being his God.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Bleſſings of the Covenant are greater than an Admiſſion to the External Seal of it, and therefore to whom God grants the greater, them he certainly eſteen's fit to receive the leſs. If Chriſt be pleaſed to make over the Bleſſings of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace to Infants, then it is his
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:38078:25"/>pleaſure they ſhould not be denyed an Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to the Seal of that Covenant, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by in the Eye of Man they may even in their Minority be received and owned as Members of him; and they when they come to Age may be ſatisfied of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception into that Covenant wherein God engaged to be their God, and they engaged to be his People.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Seal properly belongs to them who have Right to the Covenant and its Bleſſings, elſe would it be ſet to a Blank. They who are not in the Covenant, not have any Right to its Bleſſings, can have no Plea for their Admiſſion to its Seal: But they who have both the former, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſurely be denyed in Juſtice this latter.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Children are capable of having Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies aſſured to them, though they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand not the act of Aſſurance, or what is Aſſured to them. We often in Civil con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns Entail Eſtates on Children, and make Proviſion for Infants even unborn, and why ſhall we in Spirituals debar them of Bleſſings, which in Gods eſteem they are capable of.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Minor. </seg>
                  </label> The other Propoſition, That Children have Right to the Bleſſings of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, will not, I ſuppoſe, be denyed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe,</p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:38078:26"/>
               <p n="1">1.
<note place="margin">Acts 2.39.</note> The Promiſes of the Covenant are made to them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Chriſt aſſures us they are his Diſciples, Heirs of the Kingdom of Heaven, and ſhall be ſaved; nay, he often propoſeth, in order to our Salvation, the imitation of them in many things,
<note place="margin">Mat. 19.14.</note> and doubtleſs, if others ſhall be beloved of God and ſaved, becauſe like Children, God will ſave, and doth love theſe whom thoſe are like. If I promiſe my Favour to one, becauſe he is like my Friend, it Argueth me to have a greater Love for my Friend, which makes me Love what is like him.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If they have no Right to the Bleſſings of the Covenant, then have they no In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in Chriſts Death, nor Right to Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, which is a ſad conſideration; and if theſe latter be granted, the former will follow.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> are forced to grant them within the Covenant of Grace, and to have Right to its Bleſſings, and to be Heirs of Heaven, elſe they fore-ſee their Doctrine would be exploded with hiffing. And certainly, if they have Right to theſe Bleſſings of the Covenant of Grace, they have a juſt Right to Baptiſm, the Seal of this Covenant, whoſe Bleſſing they are.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The Conceſſion of our Adverſaries proves their having Right to all the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:38078:26"/>of the Covenant, in that they believe all Children dying ſo, though un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptized, ſhall be ſaved; and then let them Anſwer why they may not be Baptized. Surely there is not more required to fit one for Baptiſm than for Salvation, if Faith and Repentance be, as they plead, neceſſary in order to Baptiſm, they are ſurely much more neceſſary to Salvation; and Children having what in Gods eſteem fits them for the greater, have ſurely what qualifies them for the leſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="argument">
               <head>ARGUMENT V. <hi>Thoſe who are Capable of being engaged in Covenant with God, are Capable of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm. But Children are Capable of being engaged in Covenant with God. Therefore Children are Capable of Baptiſm.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Major. </seg>
                  </label> IN this Argument the Major ſeems un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniable, and certainly they will grant, that thoſe who are capable of being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged in Covenant with God, are capable of Baptiſm: Becauſe by Baptiſm a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant is made between God and the Soul, whereby the Perſon Baptized Covenants to be Gods Faithful and Conſtant Souldier
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:38078:27"/>and Servant. And God Promiſeth or Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venants to be the God of that Soul and of its Seed, according to the Tenor of the Covenant of Grace. And,</p>
               <p>That Children are capable of being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged in Covenant with God,
<note place="margin">Minor proved.</note> will be eaſily granted from the conſideration of theſe Reaſons.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That Children are in the Power of the Parent to diſpoſe of, as to Temporals and Spirituals.</p>
               <p n="1">1. As to Temporals, what is more uſual than to take a Leaſe for our own and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens Uſe,
<note place="margin">Deut. 6.7. Epheſ. 6.1, 4.</note> to enſure an Eſtate to our ſelves and Children, and to engage our Children. to perform Covenants, or pay Debts, who are thereby, by the Law of God and Man engaged to perform the Covenants to their Power and Ability, if Lawful and Honeſt, or elſe to loſe the Benefits that might accrue to them by Obſervance of that Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As to Spirituals, Parents are Obliged to take the greateſt care imaginable of their Childrens Souls,
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 6.1, 4.</note> for their Education in the Fear of God, who alſo hath commanded the Parents to engage their Children in Covenant with him, and to bring them up in his Service.</p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:38078:27"/>
               <p n="2">2. God eſteems Children capable of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaging in Covenant with him,
<note place="margin">Deur. 29 11, 12, 14. Rom. 10.5. <hi>to</hi> 10. Deut. 30.11, 12, 13, 14</note> and gives command for all the Little Ones to ſtand before him to be entred into Covenant with him, who were as capable of being engaged in Gods eſteem, and were as much engaged as thoſe Captains, Men, and Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, that ſtood with them, and were not engaged in Covenant, as was once imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinently urged to me by our Adverſaries, from a Critical Obſervance of the Particle <hi>Thou;</hi> as if one alone in the ſtead of all others had been engaged: To which Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticiſm I returned (beſides the premiſed Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of Childrens being equally capable of being engaged as all the others, who being preſent were not engaged, and that the engagement of one in ſtead of all did no more infringe the capability of Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren then it did that of thoſe Captains, Men, Women, who were by, and not engaged) that I thought the Particle <hi>Thou,</hi> might reaſonably refer to every individual Captain, Man, Woman, and Little One, who I ſuppoſe to have been particularly concern'd, and the Commandments were inſtanced in, which concern all, yet are given in the ſame ſecond Perſon ſingular. Nor was this Covenant any other than a Covenant of Grace, the ſame Covenant now remaining as to its ſubſtance, only
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:38078:28"/>freed from the encumbring Ceremonies, and altered as to its External Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of its Miniſtry, Sacrifices, Baptiſm, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as hath been proved, and the Marginal Citations compared, will manifeſt.</p>
               <p n="3">3.
<note place="margin">2 Chron 20.13. Joel 2.16. Deut. 31.11, 12, 13.</note> The <hi>Jews</hi> Children were formerly concerned in the Duties of the Covenant, as in Faſting, Prayer, and God accepted of them as capable of entring into Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, of Hearing, Learning, Doing his Will; ſurely then we may eſteem ſo.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Our Children are as capable now as the Children of the <hi>Jews</hi> were then; nor can an Objection be againſt ours, but it is equally valid againſt theirs; and if God accepted theirs, we have the ſame Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and God of Mercy, and ſo the ſame Reaſon to believe he will receive ours; and then why ſhould we eſteem them uncapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of being engaged in Covenant with God by Baptiſm?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="argument">
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:38078:28"/>
               <head>ARGUMENT VI. <hi>Thoſe who are Members of Chriſts Church ought to be Baptized. But Children are Members of Chriſts Church. Therefore Children ought to be Baptized.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THIS Argument hath no ſmall force in it, as will appear by conſidering each Propoſition diſtinctly.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Major. </seg>
                  </label> Thoſe who are Members of Chriſts Church ought to be Baptized, as appears,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe this is the uſual way of Solemn Admiſſion into Chriſts Church,
<note place="margin">Acts 2.37, 38,</note> and the Apoſtles uſually Practiſed thus, Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring Baptiſm upon their receiving any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Church of Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If Baptiſm be not Adminiſtred at the Admiſſion of Perſons into Chriſts Church, then muſt it be done after, or not at all: The laſt is not true, Chriſts Ordinance ought not to be neglected; and there is no Inſtance or Precept in Scripture what time after a Perſons Converſion, and becoming a Church-Member, it ſhould be done: Therefore it muſt be done as the Apoſtles Practiſed it at the Receiving any into the Church of Chriſt.</p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:38078:29"/>
               <p n="3">3. Our Adverſaries, the <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> acknowledge none Members of a Viſible Church of Chriſt but thoſe who are Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, and Baptize (as they call it) thoſe whom they receive as Church-members, at their firſt Admiſſion, whence directly follows from their own Practice, that thoſe who are Church-members ought to be Baptized.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Chriſts Church is to be Purified with the waſhing of Water by the Word:
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.26.</note> If then Children are of his Church, they ought to be Baptized.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Minor. </seg>
                  </label> And that Children are Members of Chriſts Church appears (as to their Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berſhip of his Inviſible Church, from our Adverſaries granting them Eternal Life, and all Priviledges belonging to ſuch Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers) and that they are alſo Members of Chriſts Viſible Church, will appear thus:</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Children of the <hi>Jews</hi> were with their Parents Church-members under the Law,
<note place="margin">Baxter's <hi>Infant Church-Memb. p.</hi> 26. Deut. 31.11, 12.</note> which Law is not yet Repealed by Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Children of the Converted <hi>Jews</hi> loſt not their Priviledges, but ſtill remained Church-members, for Chriſt did not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fringe, but rather enlarge the Priviledges of his People. And St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſeems to uſe this as a great motive to induce the <hi>Jews</hi> to cloſe with Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Acts 2.37, 38, 39.</note> that though they had
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:38078:29"/>Crucified the Lord of Life, their Promiſed and Expected <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> yet they Repenting and being Baptized, might be ſaved, and might find Mercy for themſelves and their Seed alſo; for the Covenant and Promiſe is ſtill to You and to your Seed.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The <hi>Gentiles</hi> are through Chriſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to equal Priviledges with the <hi>Jews;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 11.11, 15, 25. Eaxter, <hi>p.</hi> 20.</note> the Children of Parents who did not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, were Excluded, therefore the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Parents believing, were received.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The <hi>Jews</hi> ſhall with their Children be recalled into a ſtate of Church-mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berſhip at their Converſion,
<note place="margin">Rom. 11.25, 26, 27.</note> therefore doubtleſs the Children of Believing and Converted <hi>Gentiles</hi> are Church-members.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Children are either Members of the Viſible Church of Chriſt, or elſe are viſibly of Satans Kingdom. There is no <hi>Medium</hi> between theſe two, all appertain either to Chriſt or Satan. Now, let them and us conſider how diſmal a Doctrine theirs is, which makes all the Children of the World of the Viſible Kingdom of Satan, and ſo denies us any good grounds for the hope of their Salvation. And how ſtrangely their Thoughts are linked together in granting Children all the Priviledges of Church-members, as Pardon of ſin, and Eternal Life, and ſo eſteem them of Chriſts Inviſible Church, and yet Excommunicate
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:38078:30"/>them out of his Viſible Church;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Art.</hi> 11. <hi>of their Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples.</hi> Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam's <hi>Works,</hi> l. 2. p. 67. c. 5.</note> and to countenance this, they calumniate Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and ſay, the Old Teſtament-way of bringing of Children into the Church is caſt out; and that Children are not mentioned as received in the New Teſtament, about which the Author Cited ſpends ſome leaves, which Calumny may eaſily be wiped off, and his leaves blown away, as to the force of their Arguments againſt us; for it can never be proved that Children are in any place by Chriſt rejected and excluded the Covenant, Diſcipleſhip, and Church-memberſhip; and it is fully proved, and muſt be granted they were in the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, were Diſciples and Church-members before Chriſt. But if by the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment-way of bringing in Children into the Church being caſt out They mean not to infringe the Priviledge of Children, the Subject of this Argument, but to ſhew the way of their Admiſſion into the Church to be altered,
<note place="margin">Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam's <hi>Chriſtians Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive,</hi> &amp;c. l. 2. p. 2. cap. 2. ſect. 2. p. 6. <hi>to</hi> 17.</note> we grant it, it being formerly done by Circumciſion, and now by Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm. As for the ſeveral Leaves premiſed, the ſum of all of them is to prove that in the Churches at <hi>Rome, Corinth, Galatia, &amp;c.</hi> to which the Apoſtles wrote, there was no mention of Children: Therefore he ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Children not to be Church-members, and to have no Right to Baptiſm. The
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:38078:30"/>force of which Arguing may be rendred invalid two ways,</p>
               <p n="1">1. By ſhewing Reaſons why Childrens Baptiſm and Church-memberſhip are not mentioned in the New Teſtament, which I ſhall do in due time.</p>
               <p n="2">2. By diſtinguiſhing between the Church then and now. Then it was in Gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and now Gathered: Then only the Heads of Families, Maſters, Parents, and other Adult Converts are written to, and taken Notice of to be Baptized,
<note place="margin">Acts 16.15, 31. 1 Cor. 1.18. 2 Tim. 4 19. Rom. 16.11, 15. 1 Cor. 16 19. 1 Theſ. 4.15.</note> and to be accounted Church-members; but yet we find whole Families Baptized, and ſeveral Saints greeted with the Church of God in ſuch an Houſe, which may as reaſonably inſer the Children and Servants of ſuch Families to have been Baptized, and to have been reckoned Church-members, and we may as reaſonably believe there were Children in ſome of their Houſes and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies who were Baptized, as they can confidently deny it. So that I ſee not what force thoſe many words in ſeveral Leaves have againſt our eſteeming Infants Church-members; and if that be granted, we have proved the Rationality of their being Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="argument">
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:38078:31"/>
               <head>ARGUMENT VII. <hi>They who are Diſciples of Chriſt may be Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized. But Children are Diſciples of Chriſt. Therefore Children may be Baptized.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IF that Propoſition of Childrens being Chriſts Diſciples be made good, none will ſurely deny them Baptiſm. Yet leſt ſuch Oppoſers may occur, I ſhall prove both Propoſitions. And,</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Major. </seg>
                  </label> That thoſe who are Diſciples of Chriſt may be Baptized, is thus proved.</p>
               <p n="1">1. This was the way of Diſcipling or Collecting Perſons out of Heatheniſm or Judaiſm to Chriſt. A diſtinguiſhing Mark between Chriſts Diſciples and Heathens or Jews. Therefore Diſciples of Chriſt may be Baptized.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Expreſs Texts of Scripture command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, eſpecially the ſubject of this preſent Diſcourſe,
<note place="margin">Mat. 28.19.</note> the words of our Saviours In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of Baptiſm being, <hi>Go Diſciple all Nations, Baptizing them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. The Apoſtles Practice was ſuitable, who Baptized all the Converts as ſoon as they were Converted,
<note place="margin">Acts 16.15, 31.</note> and ſo became Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples. And by this treble cord may our
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:38078:31"/>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Minor. </seg>
                  </label> Adverſaries be drawn to ſee Baptiſm duly applicable to thoſe who are Diſciples, which Children will appear to be, thus.</p>
               <p>Children are Diſciples of Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="1">1. God and Chriſt owns them as ſuch.
<note place="margin">Acts 15.1, 2, 10.</note> The Yoak that the <hi>Jews</hi> would have laid upon the new Converted <hi>Gentiles</hi> was Circumciſion, which pertained to Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren who were to be Circumciſed the Eighth Day, and yet is laid too upon the Diſciples Necks. Nor was it an caſie Yoak, but might admit of what the Texts ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe about it, that it was a Yoak which neither they nor their Fathers were able to bear. <hi>Moſes</hi> was called by his Wife,
<note place="margin">Exod. 4.25. Gen. 34.24, 25.</note> A Bloody Husband, becauſe of it. And the <hi>Shechemites</hi> found it an intolerable Yoak, in that they were ſlain, when Circumciſed, before they were whole.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They are Diſciples, in that though Man cannot Teach them, yet God can, and may, yea, he hath given us ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of his Teaching ſeveral from the Womb: It is not in the Power of the moſt Eloquent Preacher by the ſtrongeſt Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, or moſt inviting Motives, to Diſciple a Soul to Chriſt without Gods co-working; who,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 6.1.</note> who, as he is pleaſed ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily to work by means, yet can, and hath wrought without means, having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved this Heart-work to himſelf. And
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:38078:32"/>he can, and hath Taught ſeveral Children, as <hi>Jeremiah</hi> and St. <hi>John</hi> may inſtance;
<note place="margin">Jer. 1.5. Luke 1.15. Iſa. 54.13. John 6.45. Acts 10.47.</note> yea, he hath promiſed to Teach them. And how dare we forbid Water to Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize thoſe who may have received the Holy Ghoſt as well as we? Nay, probably may be more Diſciples of Chriſt than our ſelves. What would this be but a ſetting our ſelves in Gods ſtead, and determining who are his Diſciples, and conſequently who ſhall be ſaved?</p>
               <p n="3">3.
<note place="margin">Luke 18.16, 17. Mat. 19.13. Luke 9.47.</note> Chriſt commands the Receiving them in his Name, and owns them as Heirs of the Kingdom of Heaven, and aſſures us, that they who receive them, receive him, which ſurely declares their Diſcipleſhip. And how know we but we may refuſe and reject a Chriſt in them by refuſing of them.</p>
               <p n="4">4. They are capable of being Subjects in Earthly Kingdoms, and Members of Chriſts Church &amp; Kingdom, are owned by God as his Servants, and then we may own them as Diſciples. And methinks the <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts,</hi> who grant to them their enjoying of thoſe Bleſſings Chriſt hath Promiſed to his Diſciples, may well account of them as Diſciples, and if that be granted, certainly it is very Reaſonable to admit them to Baptiſm.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="argument">
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:38078:32"/>
               <head>ARGUMENT VIII. <hi>To whom Chriſt grants impoſition of Hands, to them be longs Baptiſm. But to Children Chriſt grants impoſition of Hands. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to them be longs Baptiſm.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THIS Argument may admit of ſome Explanation, my Deſign being here to introduce Scripture, and Chriſts Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample. It was between Chriſt and his Apoſtles, as between Superiour and Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour Miniſters in the Church, Chriſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed the chiefeſt, they the other Offices in the Church and Miniſtry. Chriſt Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized none himſelf, the Apoſtles Baptized,
<note place="margin">John 4.2.</note> and he Confirmed, or laid Hands on the Baptized. So that if Chriſt grant impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Hands to Children, it in the Order of Ordinances preſuppoſeth their Baptiſm, or cap city for Baptiſm; becauſe,</p>
               <p n="1">1.
<note place="margin">Heb. 6.2.</note> In the Order of Ordinances impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Hands, or Confirmation ſucceeds Baptiſm.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It is a Confirmation by a Superiour of the Truth of that Doctrine into which the Perſon was Baptized by an Inferiour Miniſter, and alſo a Teſtifying of the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:38078:33"/>receiving the Baptized Perſon into Chriſts Church.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The very <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> Practice impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of Hands after Baptiſm, as likewiſe did the Apoſtles, and all Chriſtian Churches do, ſo that from the Practice of themſelves I preſume they will grant thoſe to have a Right to Baptiſm that are capable of being admitted to the other Ordinance of Laying on of Hands.</p>
               <p>Therefore I ſhall prove my <hi>Minor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That Chriſt granted impoſition of Hands to Children, which appears,</p>
               <p n="1">1. From the expreſs Texts declaring the Subject on whom Chriſt laid Hands, which was not Adult Perſons,
<note place="margin">Mat. 19.13, 14, 15. Mark 10.13, 16.</note> Men and Women, but by the Teſtimony of two Evangeliſts, little Children: They were <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which is a diminutive of <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and denotes little, little Children; and indeed the Geſture of Chriſt towards them declares as much, in that be took them up in his Arms; nor is the Action of the People inconſiderable in this matter, who brought them to Chriſt, both which imply they were Little Ones, who could not come alone, elſe need they not to have been brought; nor ſtand alone, elſe Chriſt might have laid his Hands on them ſtanding, without taking them up into his Arms.</p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:38078:33"/>
               <p n="2">2. The Ordinance it ſelf declares it, it was impoſition of Hands; <hi>Chriſt laid his hands on them, and Bleſſed them,</hi> ſaith the Text, which</p>
               <p n="1">1.
<note place="margin">Heb. 6.2.</note> Is in the very words the Holy Ghoſt expreſſeth that Ordinance of Chriſts Church, Confirmation, both in the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Text and our Tranſiation,
<note place="margin">Mar. 19.15.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>laying on of Hands. And Chriſt laid his hands on them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. That this impoſition of Hands was an Ordinance and no common Laying on of Hands, may eaſily be gathered, becauſe here is no mention of the Childrens being ill, or labouring under any Malady, to be Cured by Chriſts touch, which might move Chriſt to lay Hands on them, in order to their Cure.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Chriſt did not at any time lay hands on, Pray, and Bleſs for the healing any Malady, as he did at this time.</p>
               <p n="4">4. It refers to a Spiritual good by our Saviours Reaſon given why he laid hands on them, <hi>Theirs, or of ſuch is the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi> They belong to my Church here, and ſhall partake with me of my Glory hereafter.</p>
               <p>Beſides this Argument, theſe Texts ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of many more for Infant Baptiſm, ſo that our Church hath Prudently choſen it as one Reaſon for its Practice, wherein is,</p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:38078:34"/>
               <p n="1">1. A double Precept tending to it, 1. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmatively, <hi>Suffer little Children to come unto me.</hi> 2. Negatively, <hi>Forbid them not.</hi> By both which our Saviour ſhews the earn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtneſs of his deſires, Children ſhould come, and his unwillingneſs they ſhould be hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, from coming to him, or becoming (as the very words import) Proſelytes of him.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It was to a viſible Mercy; Chriſt could have beſtowed on them Internal Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, nor could his Diſciples have hindred them from receiving them, or from being Members of Chriſts Inviſible Church, but becauſe they obſtructed their coming to Chriſt to accept of a Viſible Mercy, and of an outward Priviledge belonging to Chriſts Viſible Church, he is diſpleaſed.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Diſpleaſure of Chriſt againſt his Diſciples for this fault is Emphatically ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed,
<note place="margin">Mark 10.14.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, He was very Angry with them, ſo as ſeverely to chide them for it, as the Publick Reproof they had declares. Let us take heed we incur not the like, by keeping from him thoſe whom he bids to be be admitted to him.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The expreſſion of Chriſt concerning the Children whom he Bleſſed, declaring [<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>] of thoſe very Infants or Children, and of their Species is the Kingdom of Heaven, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it includes the preſent ſtate of
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:38078:34"/>Grace, and the future ſtate of Glory.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Their coming to Chriſt is their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming his Diſciples or Proſelytes, <hi>Suffer them,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, to be Proſelytes to Me, or let them be received as my Diſciples. And how can Children be brought to Chriſt, or come to be his Proſelytes and Diſciples under a Goſpel Oeconomy, unleſs by Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, as the <hi>Jews</hi> were formerly under the Law by Circumciſion.</p>
               <p>This Text rightly conſidered might ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence all Oppoſers, and gain their conſent to our Practice.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="argument">
               <head>ARGUMENT IX. <hi>If the Faith of the Parents entitles the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to the Covenant, it entitles them to Baptiſm. But the Faith of the Parents entitles the Children to the Covenant. Therefore the Faith of the Parents entitles the Children to Baptiſm.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN this Argument, the Grand Enquiry is, the Benefits reſulting to the Children of Believing Parents, from their Parents Believing. And it being manifeſted that the Parents Faith entitles the Children to the Covenant, we have Proved the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:38078:35"/>That they being in Covenant, ought to be Baptized.</p>
               <p>And that the Faith of the Parent doth entitle Children to the Covenant and its Bleſſings and Priviledges, I thus Prove,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Scriptures ſeem clear in it, when St. <hi>Peter</hi> had Converted the <hi>Jews,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 2.37, 38, 39.</note> he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth to them, a Believing on Chriſt, and adds the Covenant then to be to them and to their Seed. And that place already urged manifeſts the Child,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 7.14.</note> though but of one Believing Parent, to be in Covenant with God, and ſo eſteemed Holy.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If Children of Believers had no Right to the Bleſſings of the Covenant, in vain are our Prayers for them; but we believe and know that our Prayers are helpful and ſerviceable to them, and obtain Bleſſings for them.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Faith of Parents amongſt the <hi>Jews</hi> entitled their Children to the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,
<note place="margin">Rom. 11.26. Deut. 29.10, 11. Gen. 17.10.</note> the Belief of the Proſelyte rendred all his Children capable of Circumciſion; and the like Promiſes and Priviledges are granted to and enjoyed by Chriſtians.</p>
               <p n="4">4. We find the Jaylor inſtructed to Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve,
<note place="margin">Acts 16.33.</note> and preſently <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, in the very ſame hour, not only him, but all with him <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> forthwith were Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized.</p>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:38078:35"/>
               <p n="5">5. Elſe there is no difference obſerved between our Children and thoſe of <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Infidels,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.12, 13.</note> but ours would be equally with theirs without Chriſt, which is a Myſtery unknown to the <hi>Jews,</hi> and a thing not to be credited by us ſince Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Lydia</hi> and the Jaylor,
<note place="margin">Acts 16.15, 31, 33. Gen. 17.7.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi> being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed, we may ſuppoſe believed the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine made known, yet on their Believing, their whole Families were Baptized, agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to what hath been premiſed concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Abraham</hi> and others, who believing among the <hi>Jews,</hi> were Circumciſed and all their Families. So that I humbly ſuppoſe we may genuinely infer from theſe Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, that Children by Right of the Faith of their Believing Parents are received in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Covenant by God, and have been, and ought to be received to the Seal of that Covenant by Man.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="argument">
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:38078:36"/>
               <head>ARGUMENT X. <hi>Thoſe who are Capable of the Kingdom of Heaven are Capable of Baptiſm. But Children are Capable of the Kingdom of Heaven. Therefore Children are Capable of Baptiſm.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Major. </seg>
                  </label> THE Major Propoſition of this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Proving their capability of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm who are capable of the Kingdom of Heaven, relyeth on theſe grounds.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The greater includes the leſs: But it is a greater thing to be fit Subjects for Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, than to be fit for Baptiſm. Many are Baptized, who ſhall not be ſaved, but all who ſhall be ſaved, are fit for and capable of Baptiſm.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Requiſites for Baptiſm are far more neceſſary to Salvation,
<note place="margin">Heb. 11.6. Rev. 21. <hi>laſt.</hi> Mark 16.16.</note> as Faith, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance; and if Children in Gods eſteem be ſuch, who are capable of enjoying Heaven as well as Believers, then ſure we may account them Subjects fit for Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Kingdom of Glory, of which they ſhall be partakers hereafter, implyeth and preſuppoſeth their being in a ſtate of
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:38078:36"/>Grace, and of the Church of Chriſt here,
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.26.</note> and if of Chriſts Church, they may be Baptized.</p>
               <p n="4">4. It ſeems unreaſonable and unchriſtian to deny an external ſign to thoſe to whom Chriſt hath granted the internal Grace, and declares he will receive to eternal Glory.</p>
               <p>So that Reaſonably it may be granted, thoſe who are capable of the Kingdom of Heaven, are capable of Baptiſm.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Minor. </seg>
                  </label> And that Children are capable of the Kingdom of Heaven, appears,</p>
               <p n="1">1. From our Saviours expreſs words,
<note place="margin">Mat. 19.15. Mark 10. Luke 18.16.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, of theſe very Children, and <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, of ſuch like Children alſo is the Kingdom of Heaven.</p>
               <p n="2">2. From the Conſert of the <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> who grant Salvation to all Children, and therefore are the more to blame to deny them Baptiſm.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="argument">
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:38078:37"/>
               <head>ARGUMENT XI. <hi>All who are Believers ought to be Baptized. But Children are Believers. Therefore Children ought to be Baptized.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Major. </seg>
                  </label> THE Major Propoſition will ſcarce be denyed by our Adverſaries, who Plead ſo much for Faith before Baptiſm. I ſhall therefore adhere to the Proof of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Minor. </seg>
                  </label> That Children are Believers. Which I thus Prove.</p>
               <p n="1">1. All to whom Chriſt will impute un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief,
<note place="margin">Mark 16.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> ſhall be damned, but according to their own Arguings, all Children ſhall be ſaved: Whence follows, that Chriſt and they eſteem them not as Unbelievers.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Chriſt expreſly calls them Believers. <hi>He took a little Child</hi> [<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>] <hi>and ſet him in the midſt of the Company,
<note place="margin">Mat. 18.5, 6. Mark 9.36.</note> and ſaid, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſhall offend one of theſe little Ones that Believe on me, it were better that a Milſtone were hanged about his Neck, and that he ſhould be ſent into the depth of the Sea.</hi> Here is a little Child, or, as the word properly ſignifies, a very little Child, and yet a Believer on Chriſt. Let us then take heed
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:38078:37"/>of offending ſuch by denying them Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, as if they were Unbelievers, becauſe we know not but that very Child we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe as an Unbeliever, may be in Gods eſteem a Believer. For,</p>
               <p n="3">3. God hath Choſen, Called, Sanctified ſome from the Womb,
<note place="margin">Jer. 1.4, 5.</note> and ſo may he have done thoſe Infants we refuſe to Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize, for ought appears to us to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary.</p>
               <p n="4">4.
<note place="margin">Luke 1.15. Rom. 5.1. John 3.16. Acts 2.39. Heb. 11.6. Bev. 21.8.</note> God grants to them what he Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to Believers. He accepts of them into Favour, imputes to them the Benefits of Chriſts Death, is the God of them, and will receive them to Heaven and Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which he would not do it he eſteemed them as Unbelievers, ſince without Faith he hath declared none can pleaſe God, or ſhall be ſaved.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Though they have not Actual Faith demonſtrable to Man, yet they may have the Seed of Faith and its habit wrought on them by God, ſince they are in his eſteem accounted as Faithful, and have the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges of Believers.</p>
               <p n="6">6. They are in Covenant with God, as we have already Proved, which Covenant is betwixt God and Believers; and if we eſteem them not as ſuch, we grant them no Priviledge as Children above the <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Pagans.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:38078:38"/>
               <p n="7">7. If only true Believers be ſubjects of Baptiſm, then is there no ſubject on whom the Miniſter can confer Baptiſm diſcernable to Men, becauſe we know not who are true Believers, and may Baptize Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, while we paſs by true Believers. And it ſeems to be an Uſurping of Gods Prerogative of Judging our Brother, in cenſuring ſome to be Unbelievers, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting them from Baptiſm, whoſe Souls may be equally Precious to God with thoſe we admit.</p>
               <p n="8">8. If the Judgment of Charity be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, and theſe ought to be Baptized, on whoſe Profeſſion of Faith we have Reaſon in Charity to think Believers. Then ſurely it is very Rational to Baptize Infants, whom in Gods and Chriſts eſteem we have Proved to be Believers, to whom they will not impute the ſin of Unbelief, on whom they are pleaſed to beſtow the Mercies promiſed to Believers, and who can neither play the Hypocrite with God,
<note place="margin">Wills <hi>againſt</hi> Danvers, p. 34. 58.</note> nor diſſemble with us; whereas Adult Perſons, whoſe Hearts we cannot ſearch, may make a Profeſſion of the Faith of Chriſt for ſome finiſter ends, and ſelf-reſpects, to affect a ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larity, and to obtain others Charity, and yet they may be Hypocritical before God.</p>
               <p>Thus have I endeavoured to Prove In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants Believers, and then according to the
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:38078:38"/>very <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> own Plea they ought to be Baptized. And here we may lament their Folly, who Diſſent from us, when as in Chriſtian Moderation Believers are Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized by us as well as them. And they having no juſt cauſe of Separation, are indeed the more culpable.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="argument">
               <head>ARGUMENT XII. <hi>They who are capable of the Ends of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, may be Baptized. But Children are capable of the Ends of Baptiſm, Therefore they may be Baptized.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE Major ſeems directly to prove Baptiſm; for if the Minor be true, That Children are capable of the Ends of Baptiſm, nothing ſeems to hinder their being Baptized. And therefore I ſhall chiefly aim to Prove Children capable of the Ends of Baptiſm, which are theſe,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Towards God, the Ends of Baptiſm are,</p>
               <p n="1">1. To be as a Covenant between God and the Soul. And Children may be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted into Covenant, their Youngneſs doth not hinder their enjoying any Mercy from God, nor deprive them of being devoted to God.</p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:38078:39"/>
               <p n="2">2. As a Seal to Ratifie the Promiſes of the Covenant, which may be applyed to Infants. We are careful to Enſure our E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates to our Children in this World; and though they be Young, yet are they not thereby deprived of their Birth-right, or rendred incapable of having an Eſtate made ſure to, or entailed upon them. And yet ſome are unwilling that God ſhould Enſure and Seal to them the Benefits of Chriſt by the Seal of the Covenant of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It is a ſign of God and Chriſts re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving Children as their Diſciples and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants,
<note place="margin">Deu. 6.6. Epheſ. 6.1, 4.</note> to which ſtate Children are capable of being admitted, and whom God hath engaged the Parents ſo to Devote.</p>
               <p n="4">4. It is a diſtinguiſhing note between Chriſtians and Heathens; but the Infancy of our Children doth not ſo incapacitate them, as we ſhould look on them but as Heathens.</p>
               <p n="5">5. It is an entring of the Soul into Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with God, to continue his Faithful Souldier and Servant to his Lifes end. And thus they are capable of being engaged, ſeeing it is the great Duty of Chriſtianity to perform it, containing nothing more than what Religion calls for. A ceaſing from ſin, and doing well.</p>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:38078:39"/>
               <p n="6">6. They are as capable of all the Ends of Baptiſm, as the Children of the <hi>Jews</hi> were capable of the Ends of Circumciſion. And then theſe may as reaſonably be Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, as they were Circumciſed.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Ends of Baptiſm, relating to Man, are,</p>
               <p n="1">1. That Parents might devote their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to Gods Service by this Baptiſmal En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement, which they are capable of, in that they are in the Power of the Parent to diſpoſe of and Educate (as God hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded) in his Fear.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That the Baptized might enjoy the Benefits of the Covenant of Grace through Chriſt, of all which Benefits, even of Heaven its ſelf, Children are capable.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That the Baptized might be amongſt Men owned and reputed as Chriſtians and Members of Chriſts Church; and this alſo Children are capable of, whom it ſeems hard to account as Heathens, when they are the Children of Chriſtians.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="argument">
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:38078:40"/>
               <head>ARGUMENT XIII. <hi>Whom the Church of Chriſt hath ever re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived to Baptiſm, may ſtill be Baptized. But the Church of Chriſt hath ever re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived Children to Baptiſm. Therefore Children may be Baptized.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AS for the Church of God among the <hi>Jews,</hi> it is evident that they received Children to Circumciſion, to which Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm ſucceeds. Nor hath the Church of Chriſt ſince its Inſtitution ever denyed Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren Baptiſm, as will appear,</p>
               <p n="1">1. In that for many hundreds of Years the Queſtion was not moved,
<note place="margin">Walkers <hi>Modeſt Plea, p.</hi> 219. <hi>to</hi> 254. Walkers <hi>Doct. of Baptiſm, p.</hi> 118.</note> nor the Point doubted of as to its Lawfulneſs. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed there was little Reaſon for ſuch a doubt, conſidering that Children were Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed under the Law, and ſo admitted into Covenant, who were equally unca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of that, as our Children are now of Baptiſm; nor was that Covenant Repeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, of Children any where excluded it, or our Priviledges by Chriſt infringed, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther enlarged.</p>
               <p n="2">2.
<note place="margin">Harmony of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion.</note> The Reformed Churches, who have eſpouſed Chriſts Doctrine moſt purely, have
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:38078:40"/>unanimouſly Practiſed it, as their ſeveral Confeſſions atteſt: And in our Nation, in our <hi>Saxon</hi> King <hi>Ina</hi>'s time,
<note place="margin">Walkers <hi>Doctrine of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm. p.</hi> 126.</note> about 692 Year of Chriſt, a Child was to be Baptized with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Thirty days, under pain of the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiture of Thirty ſhillings.</p>
               <p n="3">3. In the ſeries of Scriptures, Hiſtory, and the Practice of the Church, what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth the Baptizing of Believers, and Sinners Confeſſing their ſins, hath reſpect to thoſe Adult Perſons Converted from <hi>Judaiſm</hi> or <hi>Gentiliſm</hi> when the Church was firſt Conſtituting: And in all Ages thoſe who were brought up unbaptized through their Parents or others Negligence, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the Ordinance,
<note place="margin">Order for Baptiſm of thoſe of Riper Years.</note> or are Converted to Chriſtianity, have given account of their Faith, and ſtill do in the Practice of our Church, before they are Baptized. But after a Church is Conſtituted, and Perſons Converted, thoſe thus in a Conſtituted Church had their Children ever eſteemed capable of being admitted to Baptiſm.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The deferring of Baptiſm amongſt the Ancients was not from their Queſtioning the Lawfulneſs of Infant Baptiſm,
<note place="margin">Walkers <hi>Modeſt Plea, in Preface.</hi>
                  </note> but from ſeveral Opinions they had about the Effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy of Baptiſm, as to the Pardon of Sins by it, and the danger of ſinning after it. So that theſe Opinions, whereof ſome might be erroneous, cannot take away
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:38078:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>what was juſtly and Lawfully Practiſed by Gods People before Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Walker's <hi>Modeſt Plea, p.</hi> 219. <hi>to</hi> 254.</note> and even from the
<note n="*" place="margin">Philpot <hi>the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr.</hi> Fox <hi>Acts v.</hi> 3. 607, 608, 609 <hi>at large.</hi>
                  </note> Apoſtles time ſince Chriſt. Therefore not only from Scripture and Reaſon, but from good Antiquity Children are Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully Baptized.</p>
               <p>This Argument drawn from Antiquity and the Practice of the Church of Chriſt for ſo many Centuries, ſo univerſally by all true Chriſtian Churches, by Reformed as well as Popiſh. Though it hath not ſo great force with the Vulgar, who are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable of the Rational deduction of its Lawfulneſs from this Practice, yet to the Judicious Chriſtian it prevails much, the Practice being no ways oppoſite to, but agreeing with Scripture, eaſily deduced from it, the receiving of the Practice by the Apoſtles implies its Practice in Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and from Him and Them hath it been received and retained in the Church to our days, and will be while Chriſt hath a Church upon Earth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="argument">
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:38078:41"/>
               <head>ARGUMENT XIV. <hi>That Doctrine which introduceth many un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian Conſequences is erroneous. But the Doctrine of the</hi> Anti-pedobaptiſts <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduceth many unchriſtian Conſequences. Therefore the Doctrine of the</hi> Anti-pedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts <hi>is erroneous.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Major. </seg>
                  </label> THE Major Propoſition muſt be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniably true. For that Doctrine that introduceth many or any unchriſtian Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences muſt needs err from the Rule of Chriſtianity.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Minor. </seg>
                  </label> The Doctrine of the <hi>Anti-pedobaptiſts,</hi> whereby they deny Baptiſm to Infants, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduceth many unchriſtian Conſequences, as appears.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It oppoſeth the whole current of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, nullifies many Scripture Promiſes and Priviledges, and deſtroys the Covenant of Grace, as the premiſed Pages manifeſt.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It reduceth the World into <hi>Gentiliſm</hi> or <hi>Heathemſm</hi> again, and makes Chriſts Church always gathering, never gathered; always inſtituting, and never eſtabliſhed.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It excludes Children the Covenant of Grace and its Seals, denies their Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:38078:42"/>or Memberſhip with Chriſt and his Church, they owning no viſible Church of Chriſt on Earth but their own Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues, and eſteem all us who are not of their way, as Perſons who are not viſible Members of Chriſt; whence we may eaſily gueſs their Charity and hopes of our Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</p>
               <p n="4">4. It introduceth genuinely a deſpair of Salvation of our Children; for we cannot have any good grounds for the hopes of Salvation of thoſe whom we think not to belong to the Covenant of Grace, ſo as to be uncapable of its Seal, out of the Church, ſo as to be unfit for Baptiſm; out of the way to Salvation, ſo as to be no Diſciples of Chriſt, nor Believers, which implies our eſteeming them as Unbelievers, whoſe end is eternal Miſery. And though they will not ſay ſo of our Children, yet I am ſure ſome of their Teachers have ſaid ſo of themſelves, that we are no viſible Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Chriſts Church, nor are in a viſible way to Salvation.</p>
               <p n="5">5. This Doctrine is injurious to Chriſt, and renders him a kind of Impoſtor, who hereby is made not a Mediator of a better Covenant than that with the <hi>Jews</hi> before him. And while he Promiſeth to admit the <hi>Gentiles</hi> to equal Priviledges through him, to what the <hi>Jews</hi> had before him,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:38078:42"/>makes both the <hi>Jews</hi> and our Priviledges leſs by the excluding the Children of us, and of all Converted <hi>Jews,</hi> the Covenant, and debarring them the Seal of it, Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, when as the <hi>Jews</hi> before their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion had their Children reckoned in the Covenant, and received to its Seal, Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion.</p>
               <p n="6">6. It equals the Children of Chriſtians with the Children of <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Heathens;</hi> and then ſure this Doctrine muſt be Erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous.</p>
               <p>The Form and Subject of Baptiſm being hitherto conſidered, and the Chriſtianity and Rationality of Infant Baptiſm decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, together with the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in reſpect of the Form, and the abſurd Conſequences of their Doctrine as to the ſubject of Baptiſm being detected, I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to conſider</p>
               <p>The Mode of Baptizing laid down by our Saviour,
<note place="margin">Third Part of Text.</note> and expreſſed in the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Baptizing them;</hi> whence the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> Plead ſolely for dipping, and account that no Baptiſm which is not ſo performed. And our Church admits in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differently of either dipping or ſprinkling. I ſhall therefore ſhew,</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Indifferency and Lawfulneſs of each Mode in Baptiſm.</p>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:38078:43"/>
               <p n="2">2. The unreaſonableneſs of that Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute neceſſity of that dipping the <hi>Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts</hi> have eſpouſed.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Reaſonableneſs of performing it by ſprinkling.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Act of dipping or ſprinkling may indifferently be uſed in Baptiſm with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out nullifying the Ordinance: As appears thus,</p>
               <p n="1">1. It is as an indifferent thing left to the Prudence of the Church of Chriſt, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to dip or ſprinkle, neither of them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing commanded, nor either abſolutely for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden by the Precept Baptizing.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It cannot nullifie Baptiſm, being but an external Ceremonial part and mode of performing it, the Form or Eſſence of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm remaining in the Baptizing of a fit Perſon in the Name of the Sacred Trinity. Therefore our Diſſenting Brethren are to blame to make our Baptiſm to be eſſentially corrupted, and not to be accounted Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, becauſe not performed by dipping. Nor is their Folly leſs deplorable, in Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating from that Church where Baptiſm is perfectly and rightly adminiſtred as to the Eſſence of it, on the account of a bare ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal mode of Adminiſtration.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The word by which the manner of Adminiſtration of this Ordinance is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> equally admits of both ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifications,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:38078:43"/>dipping and ſprinkling,
<note place="margin">Walker's <hi>Doctrine of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing,</hi> p. 6. <hi>to</hi> 64.</note> as is granted by the beſt Criticks, and is obvious to the Obſervant Eye of any Intelligent Reader of Sacred Writ, in too many places to be cited, as the Marginal citation at large proves. Either Act then may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended by Chriſt in the Word, and be Practiſed by Chriſts People in the Church.</p>
               <p n="4">4.
<note place="margin">Num. 19.18. Exod. 12.7. Heb. 9.13. Heb. 10.22. Rom. 6.3, 4. Col. 2.11.</note> The Sacramental Waſhings under the Law were by both dipping and ſprinkling, which might Typifie the Indifferency of either in our Baptizing.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Both anſwer what is ſignified by Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm. A Waſhing or Purifying from ſins, filth, and an evil Conſcience; and a Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying with Chriſt in Baptiſm; which place, though Objected againſt us, hath little or no force in it againſt our Practice. For,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Earth is poured on the dead Body in its Burial, and it is not put under the Earth. Therefore this rather Pleads for our Practiſe of puring Water on the Baptized Perſon, than for its being dipped or plunged under Water.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If it be urged that the Perſon Buried is under the Earth, therefore the Baptized Perſon, in conformity to his being Buried with Chriſt by Baptiſm, ſhould be under the Water. I Anſwer, that the Interred Corps is but under part of the Earth, and the Baptized Perſon by our Adverſaries can
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:38078:44"/>plead no more than being under part of the Water wherein he was Baptized; and the Child or Perſon Baptized by us is under part of Water, alſo being under that Water which is ſprinkled or thrown upon it.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Alluſion reſpects more the Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Ends of Baptiſm than a Litteral ſenſe, and implies the Baptized ought to dye to Sin, and live to Righteouſneſs; not muſt a literal ſenſe be ſtrictly underſtood, for then in conformity to our Saviours Burial, the Perſon might reaſonably Quaery, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he ought not to be part of three days under Water,
<note place="margin">Rom. 6.</note> as Chriſt was in the Grave, which would gain few Proſelytes. And as to the Spiritual ends of Baptiſm, which St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſeems to tell us is the meaning of the place.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Each Action of dipping or ſprinkling is equally Obliging: Nor is a Perſon more engaged to Obſerve them who is dipped, than he who is ſprinkled; as in the Lords Supper, a Morſel of Bread, and a ſmall quantity of Wine received is equally Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liging of the Communicant as an whole Loaf, or a full draught, unleſs we make the inward Grace, or outward Obligation of the Sacraments depend upon the Mode of an outward Adminiſtration, which is unreaſonable, and unchriſtian. Therefore either dipping or ſprinkling may be indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferently uſed.</p>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:38078:44"/>
               <p>To require Dipping as ſo abſolutely ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary in Baptiſm,
<note place="margin">Dipping not abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary.</note> that the Ordinance is null unleſs ſo performed (as the <hi>Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt</hi> pleads) is an unreaſonable Error. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe,</p>
               <p n="1">1. There is not one place of Scripture which in expreſs words commands dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping. And here they are much to blame, who while they cry out againſt us for want of Scripture-proof for Infant Baptiſm (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of this Treatiſe hath endeavoured to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt us not deſtitute.) Adhere to the Practice of this Mode of Baptizing by dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, without the leaſt command in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and yet with ſo great Zeal or Preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, as to declare us unbaptized Perſons, becauſe not dipt; when as our Saviours Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, and the Apoſtles Practice was to Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize, which word admits of both ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, nor is it mentioned by which they did it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. This is to Idolize a Ceremony, and make that the whole of Baptiſm, which is but an outward circumſtance of the Act, not determined by Chriſt, but left indifferently to his Church to be uſed, nor were obliging to the Soul, nor more repreſenting the ends of Baptiſm to the Soul than ſprinkling.</p>
               <p n="3">3. This Act cannot be uſed in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of Baptiſm in all parts of the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitable World, there being many places
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:38078:45"/>where ſo much Water cannot be gotten for many Miles together, as will ſuffice for the dipping of Perſons over Head and Ears; as in hot Countrys and Mountainous Places: Nor is it conſiſtent with Chriſtian prudence to ſuppoſe Chriſt would limit ſuch an Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance to ſuch an Adminiſtration as could not be in all places at all times performed. Nor indeed doth he, for by his Commanding on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to Baptize, he limits the act to neither Dipping nor Sprinkling but the word ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting of both, he leaves it to the prudence of his people to uſe which was moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient, who might probably in all habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Towns get ſo much water as might ſuffice to Sprinkle, though perhaps not ſo much as might ſerve to dip Perſons in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Dipping or plunging the body over Head and Ears,
<note place="margin">Baxters <hi>Infant Church-member.</hi> Walkers <hi>Doctrine of Bapt. cap.</hi> 10. <hi>p.</hi> 179.</note> ſeems to be an indecent action while either it is performed naked, or in tranſparent Garments too ſuequently, an act through the pravity of our Hearts too apt to create ſuch thoughts, as become not the Sacredneſs of the Ordinance, whence ſome had made it a Breach of the Seventh Commandment.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Nor is it a little injurious to the body, expoſing it by reaſon of the cold tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Climate, to not a few diſtempers in our Nation. But, as one obſerves, the
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:38078:45"/>Adverſary is ſo Carnally Prudent,
<note place="margin">Wills <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt</hi> Danvers.</note> as not to Practice their Baptizing till warm Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. But how conſonant to Chriſts Rule, let all judge who know it was the Practice of the Apoſtles uſually to Baptize Converts immediately upon their Converſion;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker's <hi>Doctrine of Bapt. cap.</hi> 8. <hi>p.</hi> 61.</note> and if that ſhould happen in Winter, in Froſt and Snow amongſt us in our Cold Region, and the Convert be plunged over Head and Ears in cold Water, who can ſuppoſe it conſiſtent with the Perſons Health? Nay, muſt we not reaſonably think it may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danger his Health and Life too, unleſs God work a Miracle in his Preſervation,
<note place="margin">Baxteſs <hi>Infant Church-member.</hi>
                  </note> whence ſome have made it a breach of the Sixth Commandment. Now, ſince Chriſt hath Commanded no ſuch Circumſtance which is ſo indecent, and may prove ſo injurious to our Bodies, they are very blame-worthy to uſe it, and the Church of Chriſt may prudently omit it.</p>
               <p n="6">6.
<note place="margin">Wills <hi>againſt</hi> Danvers, p. 260.</note> Plunging or dipping the Perſon Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized over Head and Ears renders him un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable of underſtanding what is done and ſaid for ſome time, ſtupifies or amazeth the Perſon, and hinders his knowing either the Perſon Adminiſtring, or the Sacrament Adminiſtred, as Experience may atteſt. Now, certainly Chriſt would have his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances performed by an external Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration, wherein the Subject might be
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:38078:46"/>in the neareſt capacity of underſtanding the ends and actions of it; and would not limit it to ſuch a Mode that is ſo injurious to the internal and external ſenſes of the Perſon under its Adminiſtration.</p>
               <p n="7">7. We cannot reaſonably think that the Apoſtles did dip all they Baptized, becauſe it was a thing of great Labour, if not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for one Man to plunge in one day Three Thouſand Perſons, as we find St. <hi>Peter</hi> Baptized.
<note place="margin">Acts 2.41.</note> So that I cannot appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend what Reaſons can be offered to ſhew the abſolute neceſſity of Dipping in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing, and I know I may ſay they have no Scripture Precept for it. Therefore I preſume to conclude. That Dipping is not abſolutely neceſſary in the Adminiſtration of Baptiſm, but it may be rightly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, though not by dipping.</p>
               <p>There remains that I ſhew the Lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Reſonableneſs of Baptizing by ſprinkling:
<note place="margin">3. <hi>Sprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful.</hi>
                  </note> Which I ſhall thus do.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Sprinkling is equally with Dipping ſignified by the word in which our Saviour expreſſed the manner of the Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this Ordinance,
<note place="margin">Wills <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt</hi> Danvers, <hi>p.</hi> 254. Walkers <hi>Doctrine of Bapt. c.</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 16. Dan. 4.3.</note> 
                  <hi>Baptize,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: Yea, and more congruous with its genuine ſignification than dipping. For <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> being a derivative, can admit of no larger ſignification than its Primitive, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:38078:46"/>which we find in the Hiſtory of <hi>Nebuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezzar,</hi> when like a Beaſt <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as the 70 renders it; He was wet with the Dew of Heaven, as our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tranſlates it: Nor can we think he was prunged over Head, or dipped in the Rain or Dew, but rather it ſeems more Rational to think that the Dew did beſprinkle him.</p>
               <p n="2">2. This Repreſents the Ends of Baptiſm as well as dipping.
<note place="margin">Acts 2.5, 6, 7.</note> The pouring out of the Holy Ghoſt was by effuſion on, not by the immerſion of the Subject. The Blood of Chriſt is applyed to us by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of ſprinkling;
<note place="margin">Heb. 9.13. Heb. 12.24. Heb. 10.22. Walkers <hi>Doct. of Baptiſm,</hi> c. 9. Exod. 12</note> and the end of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Buried with Chriſt, hath already been proved, anſwered in our being ſprinkled.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Texts of Analogy confirm its Ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nality, wherein the Type under the Law, and the thing Typified under the Goſpel by Baptiſm, are declared by ſprinkling.</p>
               <p n="4">4. There is no Vertue or Efficacy to be placed in the Element more largely Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred, to confer Grace, or oblige us: But ſprinkling as well as dipping being a ſubmiſſion to the Element, equally Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful by Chriſts Command, it is equally offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacious and ſignificant.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Sprinkling renders the Sacrament ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of being Adminiſtred at all times, in all places, without that indecency and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger dipping, as I have proved, is guilty of.</p>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:38078:47"/>
               <p n="6">6. The Church of Chriſt was never con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined to that Mode of dipping,
<note place="margin">Walkers <hi>Doct. of Baptiſm,</hi> c. 10. <hi>p.</hi> 74. <hi>to</hi> 158</note> but had ſeveral ways of Baptizing, dipping or ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. Whereby may appear the freedom of the Church of Chriſt in the indifferent uſe of dipping or ſprinkling, and the Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of our Church may be ſeen agreeable with other Chriſtian Churches. So that the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> extreamly err in account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us as unbaptized, and in nullifying our Ordinance of Baptiſm, becauſe not Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred by dipping, which is not ſo ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely neceſſary in the Adminiſtration of it, but that ſprinkling may be Lawfully uſed, as I have endeavoured to prove.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>1</label> But they Object, firſt, That our Saviour is ſaid, when he went to be Baptized, to go to <hi>Jordan,</hi> and after Baptiſm, to go up out of the Water, which implies his being dipt in the Water. To which I Anſwer,</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> 1. Chriſts going to <hi>Jordan</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> to <hi>Jordan,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 3.13.</note> declares not his going into the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, but as it is Tranſlated, to the River.</p>
               <p n="2">2. His aſcent after Baptiſm is not <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, out of the Water, but <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as from the Water, which doth not at all infer his being in the Water: But ſince the Rivers are in Valleys, a Perſon going to the River, may well be ſaid (as Chriſt is ſaid) to go down to the River. And that other trite place Objected againſt us con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:38078:47"/>
                  <hi>Philip</hi> and the Eunuch,
<note place="margin">Acts 8.38.</note> which is Tranſlated, they both went down into the Water is expreſſed thus, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, they both went down to the Water; the Prepoſition <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſignifying <hi>ad,</hi> to, as well as into, and ſo it reſpects rather the Mountainous place they went down to the Water-ſide from, than their going into the Water. And ſo Chriſts aſcent (after Baptiſm) up out of the Water being <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſignifies no more than his going up from the Water-ſide.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Though we grant Chriſt and the Eunuch did go into the Water, yet cannot it thence be inferred that they were Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized by dipping, whereof there is not one Syllable in the Text, nor any other place of Sacred Writ, nor any thing to favour ſuch an Opinion. And to deduce ſuch a Conſequence from the Text, Chriſt and the Eunuch went into the Water at their Baptizing, therefore they were dipped or plunged over Head and Ears, as it is ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, ſo is a far more remote and diſ-inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuous Conſequence than our moſt remote Concluſions for Infant Baptiſm.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>2</label> But they Object again, that St. <hi>John</hi> Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized in <hi>Enon</hi> near <hi>Salim,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">John 3.23.</note> and the Reaſon is given, becauſe there was much Water there.</p>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:38078:48"/>
               <p>To which I Anſwer,</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> 1. St. <hi>John</hi>'s determining a place for Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm was reſpecting the Commodiouſneſs for the new Converts, who might come thither, as to a place appointed for that purpoſe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. There being much Water there, made it a fit place for the Baptizing the Numerous Company of Converts reſorting thither to be Baptized.</p>
               <p n="3">3. This doth not infer their being dipt and plunged in their being Baptized there;
<note place="margin">Wilſon's <hi>Chriſtian Dictiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry on</hi> Enon. Heylin's <hi>Coſmog. in loc.</hi>
                  </note> for <hi>Enon</hi> in its ſignification denotes but a little Fountain, and being near the River <hi>Jordan,</hi> it is ſaid to have much Water by reaſon of the ſcarcity of that Element in that Countrey, part of <hi>Jordan</hi> its ſelf being uſually dry in Summer time, and <hi>Jordan</hi> its ſelf, that Famous River, was not Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vigably deep. And the Water by <hi>Enon</hi> is by others accounted as a little Foord, over which one might ſtride or leap; or how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever not containing ſo much Water as might fit it to dip or plunge over Head and Ears ſo many as were in thoſe days Baptized.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The expreſſion of much Water being thus, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſignifying many Waters, denoting the confluence of thoſe two Springs or Waters, <hi>Jordan</hi> and <hi>Jalor,</hi> cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing rather ſome Stream, rather than ſo
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:38078:48"/>much as might ſuffice to dip or plunge Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in; for it is not <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> nor <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, to ſignifie there was much Water. And had it been ſo expreſſed, according as our Tranſlation renders it, yet a little Stream may be eſteemed much Water in that hot and dry Countrey, whoſe Famous River <hi>Jordan</hi> was not Navigable, and therefore it ſelf almoſt incapable of ſerving to the dipping of ſo many as were Baptized.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Suppoſing it to be a place of much Water, and that it was fit for Perſons to be dipt or plunged in it, yet there being no mention at all of ſuch a dipping or plung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but only that St. <hi>John</hi> Baptized there, it can give no colour to the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> for their dipping whom they Baptize. Nor can it be deduced from thence, the force of their Objection lying in there being there much Water, only denotes the fitneſs of the place to Baptize the many Converts in, and gives an equal Latitude for Baptizing them by pouring water on them at the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſide, as it doth for dipping them in the River, for which Practice the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> are wholly deſtitute of Scripture Precept or Preſident, and are therefore blame-worthy to Separate from our Church without Cauſe, Baptiſm being rightly Adminiſtred by us according to that due form, on that fit Subject, and after that Lawful manner Chriſt appointed.</p>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:38078:49"/>
               <p>Thus have I performed the deſign of the Text, and diſcovered the Neceſſity, Form, Subject, and Manner of Baptiſm. It remains Laſtly, that I Anſwer thoſe En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiries made by the <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> as Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections againſt things pertaining to our Practice. As,</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Enq. </seg>1</label> 
                  <hi>If Infant Baptiſm was Lawful, Chriſt or his Apoſtles would have Commanded and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed it: And if Lawful, why is it not men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in Scripture?</hi> To this I Anſwer,</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> 1. Chriſt is expreſly ſaid to have Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized none,
<note place="margin">John 4.2. John 3.22.</note> nor muſt that in <hi>John</hi> 3. op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe this, ſo as to render it untrue; for Chriſt did Baptize as he Ordered his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles to do it, and did it by them, but in his own Perſon himſelf Baptized none; yet did Chriſt grant to Children what was greater than Baptiſm, the Holy Ghoſt and Eternal Life, and admits them to the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of Laying on of Hands, which preſuppoſeth their being Baptized, as hath been largely proved.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Conſequence is invalid, <hi>a non dicto ad non factum,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">John 21.25.</note> for St. <hi>John</hi> acquaints us many things were done by Chriſt and his Apoſtles that are not written, and ſo might this be Practiſed, though not expreſſed.</p>
               <p n="3">3. As great Eſſential matters to the Church of Chriſt are not expreſſed either by way of Precept or Practice in Scriptures. The whole
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:38078:49"/>Scriptures afford not one Inſtance of a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans Receiving the Lords Supper, or of the Apoſtles themſelves being Baptized, or of any Children of Believers or Converts being at any Age Baptized, but it ſolely relates the Baptiſm of Heathens when Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted to Chriſt, or of Jews embracing Chriſt as their <hi>Meſſiah.</hi> But yet we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve on good grounds that Women ought and may partake of the Lords Supper, and that the Apoſtles of Chriſt were Baptized, and that Baptiſm is as neceſſary to be Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed by, and upon the Poſterity, Seed, and Children of Believers and Profeſſing Chriſtians, as it was upon the new Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted <hi>Jew</hi> or <hi>Gentile,</hi> though theſe and other things as material be not mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in Scripture.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> who put this En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry to us, as if nothing ought to be done but what is the expreſs Precept of, or Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident in Scripture, do themſelves Practice Baptizing by Dipping, without any Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Precept or Example.</p>
               <p n="5">5.
<note place="margin">Gen. 17.</note> It was largely Commanded in the Old Teſtament, that the Children of Gods People ſhould be, and they were alſo ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted unto the Seal of the Covenant, Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion; and Chriſt abundantly mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſts our Priviledges to be as great as theirs,
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.13, 19. Heb. 8.6.</note> whence, as we have proved at large,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:38078:50"/>directly follows our Childrens Right to Baptiſm.</p>
               <p n="6">6. There needed no new Command for it, Chriſt being a Saviour to <hi>Jew</hi> as well as <hi>Gentile,</hi> and admitting both to equal Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges, would not, did not abrogate any of the <hi>Jews</hi> Priviledges they enjoyed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his coming; nor did Chriſt ſpeak one Syllable againſt their Childrens Baptiſm, but only gave Precepts for the Collecting a Church of both <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Gentile</hi> by Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving in him, and being Baptized into the Faith of him: And the Covenant between God and the <hi>Jews</hi> through their <hi>Meſſiah</hi> to come, being un-repealed by him when come, ſtill gives the Children of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> (they having equal Priviledges) right to Baptiſm, which is warrantably Practiſed, nor can it be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful, it being againſt no Law, and ſo not an <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p n="7">7.
<note place="margin">1 Joh. 3.4. Mat. 19.13, 14, 15.</note> All the Spiritual and Eternal Mercies the Covenant of Grace contains, and Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm Seals, are expreſly Promiſed and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed in the Scriptures of the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to Children.</p>
               <p n="8">8. It is more than probable that Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren were Baptized, in that we Read of ſeveral whole Families Baptized by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, and that only on the account of the Parents or Maſters Profeſſing the Faith.
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:38078:50"/>
                  <hi>Abraham</hi> Believed, and he and all his,
<note place="margin">Gen. 17. Acts 16.15, 31, 34. 1 Cor. 1.16.</note> 
                  <hi>Iſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mael</hi> and <hi>Iſaac, &amp;c.</hi> were Circumciſed: The Jaylor, <hi>Lydia, Stephanas,</hi> &amp;c. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, and preſently they and their whole Families and Houſholds are Baptized; whence we have Infant Baptiſm tacitly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed in Scripture.</p>
               <p n="9">9. And Laſtly, Scripture is ſilent as to a Precept for Infant Baptiſm under the New Teſtament Diſpenſation, becauſe it was the Practice of <hi>Jews</hi> to Baptize their Proſelytes, both Parents and Children (as we have proved) though not Sacramentally till Chriſts Commiſſion for it: So there needed not a New Command to promote an Old Practice, continued from <hi>Abraham</hi>'s time to Chriſt, and no ways by him or his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles ſpoken againſt; only there needed a Precept and Commiſſion from Chriſt to make thoſe Baptiſmal waſhings to be a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of his Goſpel Church,
<note place="margin">Mat. 28.19, 20.</note> which was done by our Saviour in the words of the Subject of this Diſcourſe, as appears in that it was not a Precept to Adminiſter Baptiſm (ſave only as to the <hi>Gentiles</hi>) becauſe it was Practiſed upon Chriſt and by St.
<note place="margin">Mat. 3.17. John 1.25, 26. John 4.1, 2.</note> 
                  <hi>John</hi> on ſeveral others before this Commiſſion was given, though by this Precept and Commiſſion it became firſt a Sacrament to both <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Centile.</hi> And theſe Reaſons may ſuffice why Infant Baptiſm is not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:38078:51"/>Commanded in Scripture. And this ſmall Treatiſe will prove the great Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons Scripture gives us to receive them to the Sacrament of Baptiſm, nor doth Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture afford any tittle againſt it. Therefore ſurely it may be Lawfully Practiſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Enq. </seg>2</label> 
                  <hi>If Children be received to Baptiſm, why are they not alſo received to the Lords Supper?</hi> I Anſwer,</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> 1. The Children of the <hi>Jews</hi> were ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to Circumciſion, but not to the Paſſeover.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Children, though capable of having Baptiſm Adminiſtred to them, yet are not capable of Manducation, or eating Bread.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Baptiſm precedes the Lords Supper, as Regeneration doth our growth in Grace; and in a Natural ſtate, a Child is firſt Born before he can be Nouriſhed externally in order to his Growth.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Though Children are capable of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm and the Sealing the Bleſſings of the Covenant of Grace to them thereby, yet are they not capable of performing the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties requiſite to be Acted by any Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicant, as ſelf-examination, and diſcerning the Lords Body.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Enq. </seg>3</label> 
                  <hi>If Infants are capable of being engaged in Covenant with God by Baptiſm, what need have they of God-fathers and God-mothers?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:38078:51"/>
               <p n="1">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> 1. I Anſwer, The <hi>Jews</hi> had at the Circumciſion of their Children ſeveral Perſons by,
<note place="margin">Godwin. <hi>Antiq. lib.</hi> 6. Buxtorf. <hi>Jud. Syn. c.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 82. Gen. 17. Iſa. 8.25. Luke 1.58. Platina <hi>in vita</hi> Hygini, Iſaack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, <hi>Chr. An.</hi> 153.</note> as Witneſſes to Teſtifie the Childs Circumciſion, and thereby its Reception as a Member of Gods Church, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mind the Child Circumciſed when it came at Age, of what a Covenant it was concerned in between God and its Soul.</p>
               <p n="2">2. We find this Practice Recorded in Scripture as Witneſſes, at the firſt Inſtitution of Circumciſion, and afterwards continued even to the Circumciſion of St. <hi>John.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. The riſe of God-fathers and God-mothers in the Chriſtian Church was taken from the Practice of the <hi>Jews</hi> before Chriſt, and was of an early Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution. Eſpecially <hi>Eyginus,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> about 153 Years after Chriſt, who conſidering the fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Perſecutions attending the Church of Chriſt, whereby the Chriſtian Parents often were taken away, and the Children brought up in Heathen Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, or Jewiſh Superſtition did Prudently order in the Church Perſons to be engaged at Baptiſm with the Parents to take care of the Childs Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that if the Natural Parents dyed, or were ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away by Perſecution; or elſe if they Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized from the Faith, or were Ignorant, and could not; or wicked, and would not bring up the Child in the Principles and Practice of the true Religion, theſe might endeavour their being ſo Educated, that Chriſtianity might be propagated, and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren brought up in the fear of God.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Nor is this contrary to Gods pleaſure,
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 6.1. Deut. 29.10, 11. Deut. 6.6 Gen. 18.19. Joſh. 24.15.</note> who Commands and Commends the Parents and Friends engaging their Children in Covenant with him; yea, their Saves and Servant were to be engaged by them to be God Servants. And we find Godly Parents and Maſters Practiſing this Duty in their Families in their ſeveral Ages.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Children are in the Power of their Parents or Guardians to engage in Civil Contracts, and to be
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:38078:52"/>Inveſted with any Priviledge or Eſtate. Therefore our Churches Prudence is Commendable in taking care that with the Child Baptized there ſhould be Perſons who ſhould ſtand in the behalf of the Child engaged to God and the Church of Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="1">1. As Witneſſes to take notice of the Childs Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception into the Church as a Member of it, and to Witneſs to the Child (the tenor of that Covenant it was engaged in) when it grows up, and that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it ſtands obliged to be a true Chriſtian. And alſo to ſatisfie the Child that it hath been Baptized, and may proceed to other Ordinances.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As Sureties to engage as much as in them lies, to ſee the Child brought up Vertuouſly, to lead a Godly and a Chriſtian Life in Principle and Practice.</p>
               <p n="3">3. As God-fathers and God-mothers to engage themſelves as it were to God, and for his ſake and cauſe, to endeavour his Religion may be promoted in the Pious Education of thoſe Children, that the ſucceeding Age as well as the preſent may ſerve him.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Sureties. God-fathers and God-mothers are now as neceſſary as ever, for though through Gods goodneſs we are not under Perſecution for the Cauſe of Chriſt, yet the ſad Schiſms and Diviſions amongſt us in Principles and the lamentable Debauchery and Profanenets in Practice of Profeſſing Chriſtians plead it neceſſary to retain this Commendable Order of our Church; and they call aloud on all who ſtand thus engaged to God and the Church for any Child or Perſons Education, that they ſpeedily and diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly labour after a diſcharge of their Duties in a dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent endeavour that thoſe they are engaged for may be reclaimed from Impiety to Holineſs, and reduced from Error and Hereſie to the true Faith. For the neglect of thoſe who are thus engaged renders the Order (though it be in it ſelf ſo good) to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted as a meer Ceremony, and as a burdenſome Circumſtance, rather to be laid aſide than continued. But were the Perſons engaged for Children thus,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:38078:52"/>Conſcientious in the diſcharge of that great Truſt they have undertaken, the great good that would thence flow to the Church of Chriſt, would make even its Enemies to be in Love with this Order and Conſtitution.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Enq. </seg>4</label> 
                  <hi>Are Infants Obliged to perform that Covenant wherein they were by Baptiſm engaged, ſince it was not their act, but the act of other Perſons in their behalf, to which they gave no Conſent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> I Anſwer. Yes, They are obliged to perform it, and that for theſe Reaſons.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Nothing was then engaged but what is Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian and Reaſonable to be done.
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 5.8. Tit. 2.11. 1 Pet. 2.11. 1 John 5 4.</note> If we would be Happy, we muſt be Holy, which is the ſum of that Covenant then entred; for Holineſs will engage our Mortifying the Fleſh, Crucifying the World, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing the Devil and all his Works: So that theſe Duties of our Baptiſmal Vow are Commanded by God in Scripture, as well as their obſervance is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged by us in Baptiſm.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Every one hath care of his own Soul, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore what was in our Childhood engaged for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and every of us, when we come to Years of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſtanding, and retain the Chriſtian Religion,
<note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.19. Tit. 2.14.</note> are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to perform; and we oguht to endeavour it, if we expect Salvation, nothing being promiſed but what our Religion obligeth to, <hi>A ceaſing from ſin, and a living the Life of Godlineſs.</hi> And here, how may the deſires of all Chriſtians be for the Chriſtian Practice of that Solemn Ordinance of Confirmation of Perſons of Ripe Years. That they being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in the Vow of Baptiſm engaged in their Childhood, may Publickly in the Congregation own that Religion they were Baptized into, and be So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly in their own Perſons engaged to the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of it. This certainly would much diſ-engage the engaged God-fathers and Mothers, and much Oblige the Catecheumen to abſtain from all ſin, and to perform all Duties, when as every Perſon in the
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:38078:53"/>Congregation is a ſeveral Witneſs of his Solemn En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement, it will ſhame him out of Sin, nor will he dare wilfully to act contrary to the Goſpel-Rules. But</p>
               <p n="3">3. A Child is frequently obliged in Civil Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts to perform what the Parent or Guardian en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged for it; as in a Bond, Leaſe, or the like, or elſe he is lyable to the Law, and debarred from re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving any Profit or Advantage by any ſuch Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract made for him. So in Spirituals, The Child is doubtleſs engaged by the Covenant made in his Name and behalf in Baptiſm, to be Holy, or elſe he will be deprived of the Benefits of this Covenant, which is Eternal Happineſs, and be expoſed to the Law and Curſe of God; for as the Commands of God obliging the Parents to engage their Children in Covenant with God, are not impertinent. So, ſince the Duties they were then engaged in are but what God by Precept to the Children when at Age expects from them: Their non-performance of that Covenant, incurs Gods Anger, and Forfeits Heaven and Happineſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> If they Labour not to perform the Duties of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Covenant, which is their Reaſonable Service. their Parents and Friends Care for the engaging them in Covenant with God, and their devoting of them to God, and their Labour in Educating them in true Chriſtianity, will Witneſs againſt them, ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravate their Sin, and add to their Torment.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:38078:53"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
